<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of learning, or, An abstract of several books lately published, as well abroad, as at home by one of the two authors of the Universal and historical bibliotheque.</title>
            <author>Lacroze, Jean Cornand de, d. ca. 1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC P2191</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12146709</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12146709</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47975)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 109:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of learning, or, An abstract of several books lately published, as well abroad, as at home by one of the two authors of the Universal and historical bibliotheque.</title>
                  <author>Lacroze, Jean Cornand de, d. ca. 1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Abel Swalle, and Timothy Childe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Jean Cornand de la Crose. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements on p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Books --  Reviews.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54947:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54947:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF LEARNING: OR, AN ABSTRACT Of Several BOOKS Lately Publiſhed, as well abroad, as at home.</p>
            <p>By one of the Two Authors of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> and <hi>Hiſtorical Bibliotheque.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Swalle,</hi> and <hi>Timothy Childe,</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> at the Weſt-End of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:54947:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54947:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Earl of <hi>DORSET</hi> and <hi>MIDDLESEX,</hi> Lord Chamberlain of Their Majeſties Houſhold.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Work does every way belong to your Lordſhip; for beſides the many Obligations your Honour has been pleas'd to lay upon me, and to adviſe me to the compoſing of it, I know not a Perſon more univerſally Learned, and more capable of Judging all ſorts of Learned Writings. I doubt not, My Lord, but your wonted Goodneſs and Affability will vouchſafe me a favourable Acceptance of this Preſent: Though I muſt acknowledge 'tis with ſome Reluctancy that I make it. There is ſo much difficulty in making Abſtracts, and one finds ſo rarely wherewith at the ſame time to Pleaſe and Inſtruct, that I can hardly hope I have done any thing worthy to be Preſented
<pb facs="tcp:54947:3"/>to ſo delicate a Judgment as your Lordſhip's. I have been unfortunate in that I write not in my own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; by which Means ſome Improprieties may eſcape, of which I am ignorant, and which I hope your Lordſhip will pardon.</p>
            <p>I preſume to offer this Eſſay to your Lordſhip, partly becauſe I have the Honour to be known to your Lordſhip by other Works; and that I hope, under your Lordſhips Patronage, to be aſſiſted for the Future, from Men of Parts and Learning, with ſomething more conſiderable, and more deſerving your Lordſhips peruſal. I am, with all Duty and Reſpect,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Moſt Humble, and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>J. D. de La Croſe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:54947:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE following Eſſay is not as one lately Publiſhed, a Tranſlation of the <hi>Journals</hi> Printed abroad; but a real Abſtract taken from the beſt Books lately Printed both at home and abroad; which, if it finds Encouragement, ſhall be continued as oft as Matter occurs, Monthly, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>'Twill be unneceſſary that I enlarge upon the great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of theſe ſort of Works; the great Encouragement they have receiv'd in <hi>Holland, France, Germany,</hi> &amp;c. does ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently evidence their Worth, and ſeem to reproach us for having ſo long neglected it. 'Tis true, it has been twice attempted here; but thoſe having been barely Tranſlations, and the Readers ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally underſtanding the Original, ſeems to be the Reaſon they were no better received.</p>
            <p>But not to detain the Reader too long, I ſhall paſs over what might be more ſaid upon this Occaſion, and proceed to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my Deſign in as few Words as may be.</p>
            <p>I deſign then to Publiſh an Abridgment of all new Books as they ſhall appear in the World; to which purpoſe, I ſhall keep a Correſpondence abroad, in order to the being furniſhed with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing rare with the firſt. But in regard this Deſign is of too large extent; that is, the abridging of every Book that is Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; eſpecially in this Age, where ſo many trifling Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies. paſs the Preſs, I ſhall chuſe only ſuch, to inſert in this
<pb facs="tcp:54947:4"/>Work, as may moſt deſerve the peruſal of the Studious Reader. I ſhall enlarge upon ſuch as ſhall publiſh any Novelty to the World, and ſuch as diſcourſe the moſt rationally upon any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and ſhall endeavour to mark out the moſt conſiderable Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, and the Places beſt writ of every Author. The Reader muſt excuſe me, if I omit giving a Judgment upon the Style and Language of Authors; which I ſhall avoid, and chuſe rather to give Account of Things than Words. I ſhall alſo, as little as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, take any Side in the Diſputes of Learned Men; or if it ſhould happen that I adhere to one Party in ſuch Diſputes, I hope the Ingenious Reader will believe it to be the Force of Reaſon and Truth that draws me to its ſide. As for thoſe Authors that fill the World with Books ill digeſted, and wherein there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be learn'd, they ought to eſteem it a Favour in being paſſed over in ſilence. <hi>Manuals of Devotions,</hi> and <hi>Sermons</hi> we ſhall but rarely take notice of; they being of ſuch general <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, ſo well known, and read almoſt in as little time as an Abſtract. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionaries, Collections, Abridgments,</hi> and ſuch like, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors must pardon us if we take no notice of: Alſo, <hi>Law-Books,</hi> Treatiſes of <hi>Practical Phyſick,</hi> or any thing too particular in one Faculty, will be improper for us to ſpeak of; for though they may be excellent in their kind, yet their Abridgment will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear but tedious and dull to any not of that Profeſſion. But I would not be thought, upon this Pretence, to excuſe my ſelf from abſtracting ſuch ingenious Treatiſes as ſhall be Publiſhed, in <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy, Natural Philoſophy, Mathematicks,</hi> &amp;c. For though ſuch Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts may indeed be unpleaſant to ſuch as underſtand them not, they muſt bear with the Evil, and remedy it, by turning over the Leaf, to a Place that pleaſes them better; for in a Work of this Nature, which is writ for all the World, and every Profeſſion, ſuch inconveniences cannot be avoided. And thus having given an Account of our Deſign, we doubt not, but all Learned and Ingenious Gentlemen will aſſist &amp; promote it, by communicating to us ſuch things as may be convenient to inſert in this our Journal; which, if
<pb facs="tcp:54947:4"/>at any time they pleaſe to direct to the Publiſher, they ſhall be thankfully received, and Publiſhed accordingly: By this we mean, in ſuch Caſes where a Perſon may have made any Diſcovery in <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophy, Phyſick, Mathematicks, Critick,</hi> or the like, and would not give themſelves the Trouble of Writing a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe upon it, if they pleaſe to communicate it to us, we ſhall give it place in our Journal, and preſerve and publiſh it to the World, better by far than if it was Printed by it ſelf. Which Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, conſidering the preſent diſcontinuance of the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Tranſactions,</hi> will not, we hope, ſeem impertinent to the Learned World.</p>
            <p>The Reader muſt excuſe the Imperfection of this firſt Eſſay, it being but a rude Dranght of what we intend for the Future, if the Author be ſo happy to ſee his Labour encouraged, and his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign favoured by the Approbation of Worthy Perſons.</p>
            <p>This is all we thought neceſſary to tell the Publick at preſent; only this we have further to ſay, That the Abſtract of the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tographia</hi> is of another Hand, and that through Inadvertency we ſent the Copy to the Printer's, without having digeſted it into proper Order; but the like Fault ſhall happen no more.</p>
            <p>We have added at the End a Catalogue of ſome Books which we intend for the next; together with ſome others, moſt eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recommendable to the Learned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. Hiſtory of <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> taken from the Medals, <hi>&amp;c. Character of this Book. The French King's Religion toward his Allies. Of his giving Peace to</hi> Europe, <hi>and taking</hi> 200 <hi>Cities by Storm. The immortal Man.</hi> French Proteſtants <hi>how reconciled to the Church of</hi> Rome. <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the</hi> French Panegyriſts. Pag. 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54947:5"/>II. A New Bibliotheque of Eccleſiaſtical Authors. <hi>An Hiſtory of the Author and his Book. Canonical Scriptures. Ancient Liturgies; whether St.</hi> Denis <hi>was ever in</hi> France? <hi>What Honour is due to the Saints? No Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Biſhops. Doctrine of the Three firſt Centuries. Of the Power of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, Invocation of Saints, Worſhip of Images, and Celibacy.</hi> Pag. 2.</item>
               <item>III. Horatius Rodellii. <hi>Whether</hi> Mecoenas <hi>was deſcended from the Kings of</hi> Etrury, Deus eſſe, Oculo irretorto, Deſcendere Vinum. Pag. 14.</item>
               <item>IV. The Comedies of <hi>Terentius,</hi> by Madam <hi>D'Acier. Character of</hi> Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus <hi>and</hi> Terentius, <hi>and their</hi> Comedies. Contaminare. <hi>New Explication of a perplex'd Paſſage in the</hi> Andria. Pag. 19.</item>
               <item>V. Cornelius Nepos, Nic. Courtin. Pag. 23.</item>
               <item>VI. Juvenalis &amp; Perſius Lud. Pratei. <hi>Paſſage of</hi> Perſius <hi>explain'd.</hi> Pag. 3.</item>
               <item>VII. A Defence of Dioceſan Epiſcopacy. <hi>Opinions of the</hi> Independents. Pag. 25.</item>
               <item>VIII. Deſcription of the United Netherlands, <hi>&amp;c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels.</hi> London <hi>bigger than all the Cities of</hi> Holland <hi>together.</hi> Pag. 27.</item>
               <item>IX. <hi>Vauban</hi>'s New Method of Fortification. <hi>Character and Contents of this Book Original of Fortification. Situation of Places to be fortified.</hi> Orillon, <hi>Flank retired, Baſtion,</hi> &amp;c. Pag. 28.</item>
               <item>X. <hi>Haver</hi>'s Oſteologia Nova, <hi>An</hi> Idea <hi>of the Formation of the</hi> Foetus, <hi>of the</hi> Perioſteum, <hi>the</hi> Bones <hi>and the</hi> Teeth. <hi>Of</hi> Growth <hi>and</hi> Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Of the</hi> Marrow. <hi>Of the</hi> Mucilage <hi>and</hi> Mucilaginous Kernels. <hi>Of the</hi> Cartilages. Pag. 33.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Ruyſchius</hi> Obſervationes Anatomico-Chirurgicae. <hi>Wonderful Cure of an</hi> Aneuriſma. <hi>Of the Membrant</hi> Hymen. Pag. 46.</item>
               <item>XI. Leonardi Plukenetii Phytographia. Pag. 42.</item>
               <item>XII. Praxis Mayerniana.. <hi>Whether the Smoak of</hi> Tabacco <hi>can reach the Brain?</hi> Pag. 47.</item>
               <item>XIII. <hi>Richerius,</hi> De Poteſtate Eccleſiae. <hi>Votes of the Third Eſtate in</hi> France <hi>againſt the Pope's Power. The Doctrine and Practice of the</hi> Gallican <hi>Church, prov'd agreeable with them. Rules to examine whether a Doctrine be orthodox or no? Whether it be lawful for the People to depoſe Princes? Of Eccleſiaſtical Power, and Excommication. Sentiments of</hi> Marſilius <hi>of</hi> Padua. <hi>Blaſphemy of Pope</hi> Gregory VII. <hi>againſt Royal Dignity.</hi> Pag. 48.</item>
               <item>XIV. An Univerſal Analyſis of Equations Pag. 53.</item>
               <item>XV. <hi>Leybourn's</hi> Curſus Mathematicus. <hi>How to know the Length of the Way which a Veſſel makes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XVI. <hi>Some Obſervations made in the great Congregation of Waters, communicated by the Honourable</hi> R. Boyle. <hi>That Sta-water is colder on the deep below, than by the Surface.</hi> Pag. 58.</item>
               <item>XVII. Inſcriptionum Antiquarum Sylloge. <hi>Whether the Daughter of the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour builded a Church to S.</hi> Agnes? <hi>Whether the Idolatry of the Heathens be excuſable?</hi> Pag. 59.</item>
               <item>XVIII. <hi>The Falſhood of Humane Vertues. Whether Subjects may rebel againſt their Kings?</hi> Pag. 62.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54947:5"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF LEARNING.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. HISTOIRE DU ROY LOUYS LE GRAND, par les Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dailles, Emblemes, Deviſes <hi>&amp;c. Hiſtory of</hi> Lewis <hi>the Great; Taken from the Medals, Emblems, Devices, Inſcriptions, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, and other Publick Monuments, Collected and Explained by Father</hi> CLAUDIUS FRANCIS MENESTRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER <hi>Jeſuit. A new Edition augmented with five Plates. Fol.</hi> Paris, 1691. F. 64.</head>
               <p>IF the Contents of this Work were anſwerable to its Title, and if the Author had given us an exact and continued Hiſtory of the Exploits of his <hi>Hero,</hi> and had proved the moſt remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Actions that were performed under his Reign, by the Medals that were coined, and other publick Monuments that were erected on that occaſion, it would without doubt have been a very uſeful Book; but nothing of all this is to be found there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for the Medals are confuſedly placed, the order of time, which is the moſt principal matter in a Hiſtory, is not well obſerv'd, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Commentary, there is only a licentious Interpretation of the <hi>Latin</hi> Inſcriptions, or ſome other trivial Circumſtances, and that too but very rarely; inſomuch that it can neither be eſteemed as an Hiſtory nor a Panegyrick, but a groſs and imperfect Collection of whatſoever could be invented by Flattery, to aggrandize the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea</hi> of a Prince that delights in Vain-Glory, and is perhaps too much addicted to the love of popular applauſe, And indeed, what can be deviſed more vain than the Medal<note n="(a)" place="margin">25.5.</note> wherein he is repreſented in the midſt of the Cities of <hi>Genoua</hi> and <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> turning the Globe of the World, on the point of his Sword, with this Motto, <q>Quod libet licet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I do whatſoever I think fit.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Altho' the Character of a Jeſuit and a Panegyriſt doth not well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with that of a ſincere Writer; never heleſs we are induc'd to believe that Father <hi>Menêtrier</hi> hath found it to be a very difficult task, to produce theſe Medals as undoubted proofs of the Hiſtorical matters and facts related by him; as being conſcious to himſelf that the greateſt part of them were founded only on Hyperbolical ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerations,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54947:6"/>or on the falſe reports of hired News mongers. As for example, it is well known to all the World, that in the War that happen'd between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> in the Year 1666, <hi>France</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſed this Commonwealth with feigned Succours; that thoſe few <hi>French</hi> Veſſels that joyned with <hi>de Ruyter,</hi> ſerved only to moleſt and perplex him, by breaking all his meaſures, or giving an account thereof to the Enemies; and that the Forces that were ſent thither by Land, marched only to eſpie out the Country, and to contrive intrigues and plots againſt them, as it afterwards appeared by the deſign which was diſcovered in the Year 1672. Therefore we may very well turn the reverſe of the Medal, and inſtead of<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>f.</hi> 13.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Bata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis terrâ marique deſenſis. Religio foederum,</hi> put <hi>Batavis terrâ marique proditis. Deriſio foederum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are others likewiſe that are abſolutely repugnant to evident matters of fact; particularly, that which is conſecrated to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, for granting peace<note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 26.3.</note> to the <hi>Hollanders</hi> whom he had <hi>Conquer'd,</hi> to the <hi>Germans</hi> whom he had <hi>every where</hi> Vanquiſhed, and almoſt to all <hi>Europe</hi> that had combined together againſt him: For without reckoning <hi>Switzerland, Italy,</hi> and the moſt part of the Princes of <hi>Germany, Poland,</hi> and <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> who were not engag'd in this quarrel; <hi>France</hi> was aſſiſted by <hi>England, Sweeden,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Colen</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> through whoſe Territories they attacked the <hi>Hollanders</hi> at unawares. Moreover in the beginning of the War, all <hi>Europe</hi> ſeemed unanimouſly to concur in promoting the ruine of the United Provinces; ſince <hi>Spain</hi> opened a paſſage to their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the Emperour for a long time ſtood ſtill as it were a Spectator; to which if we add the Intelligence that the <hi>French</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd within the Country, and the Cowardiſe of ſome of thoſe that had the Command of the Principal Poſts, it may well be concluded from thence, that theſe Conqueſts are not ſo Glorious as they would have them to be believed. But on the contrary, there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crues to King <hi>William</hi> Everlaſting Glory, which cannot be eclipſed by the moſt inveterate Envy, for reſcuing by his Valour and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, at the Age of about 22 Years, four Great Provinces out of the Hands of ſo Haughty and Potent an Enemy; and reſtoring his Country, that was almoſt ruin'd, to its Primitive ſtate and luſtre.</p>
               <p>Theſe are matters of fact that cannot be call'd in queſtion, but we ſhall leave it to the Readers judgment to determine, whether theſe are of the like nature that afford the Subject of this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>f.</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Victori perpetuo. Ob expugnatas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbes ducentas. To the Eternal
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54947:6"/>Conqueror for having taken by Storm</hi> 200 <hi>Cities.</hi> I know not how it can be affirmed that Cities which have ſurrendred themſelves, as ſoon as the Enemy appear'd before their Gates; or thoſe that went forth to meet him, and to deliver their Keys into his poſſeſſion, were taken by force of Arms: <hi>[expugnatae.]</hi> But I am of opinion that it would be very difficult to reckon up twenty, whereof the <hi>French</hi> King hath made himſelf Maſter after another manner, at leaſt before the breaking of the Truce.</p>
               <p>The word <hi>Perpetuus,</hi> which Father <hi>Menêtrier</hi> tranſlates <hi>Eternal,</hi> calls to my remembrance the<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>f.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Viro Immortali,</hi> and the<note n="(e)" place="margin">10.6.27.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Aeternitas Imperii Gallici.</hi> The former Epithete hath been generally exploded, and it hath been very ill reſented that they durſt preſume to call <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. <hi>The Immortal Man: The Eternity of the</hi> French <hi>Empire</hi> does not appear to me to be more tolerable, and to ſay the truth, both the Expreſſions ſavour too much of Paganiſm and Blaſphemy; as well as this Counter, wherein <hi>Joſhua</hi> is repreſented giving a Signal to the Sun to ſtop, and the <hi>French</hi> King doing the like to the New Moon, with theſe words<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>f.</hi> 37.42.</note> 
                  <hi>Solem ille, hic Lunam ſiſtit,</hi> and under the Medal <hi>Germaniae Pax.</hi> However, the <hi>Germans</hi> are not willing to allow that his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty ſhould aſſume to himſelf the Glory of ſetting Bounds to the Progreſs of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and of reſtoring Peace to the Empire; but if this power be diſputed, none will deny him the honour of exciting thoſe Inſidels to break the Truce with the Emperor, and of furniſhing them with Officers, Arms, and Ammunition.</p>
               <p>Amongſt ſo many prevarications, it was not expected to find a publick Affirmation of a matter of fact, which the <hi>French</hi> Writers have for a long time diſowned, that is to ſay, that the Proteſtants of that Kingdom had not been reconciled to the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but by making uſe of the utmoſt extremity. For what elſe can be meant by<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>f.</hi> 50.</note> the labours of <hi>Hercules</hi> placed in the Conſtellations: The Thunder with theſe words, <hi>Deorum jura tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etur;</hi> the Giants cruſh'd to pieces under the Mountains; the <hi>Hydra</hi> ſlain; the heads of this Monſter ſever'd and burnt; Trees cut down; and their Branches lopt off. Nay they confeſs, that thoſe pretended Converſions could not be otherwiſe performed; in a Device, the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy whereof is the <hi>Gordian</hi> Knot cut aſunder with a Sword, and the Motto <hi>Fruſtra tentaſſent alii: Others would have attempted it in vain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Father <hi>Menétrier</hi> ingeniouſly explains the meaning of it, without any evaſion, having caus'd the<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>f.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Titles of 36 Declarations pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54947:7"/>at ſeveral times againſt the Reformed, to be grav'd on a Plate.</p>
               <p>The Printers of <hi>Holland</hi> have added to their Edition of this Work, five new Plates, comprehending divers very Satyrical Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems and Devices, which I ſhall not here mention: but only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that one M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dal groſly reflects on the Honour of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Notwithſtanding this Book taken all together, deſerves a place in the Library of the ingenious, not only on the account of ſeveral publick Monuments therein contained, as the proſpect of the Square call'd <hi>la Place des Victoires,</hi> the Obelisk of <hi>Arles,</hi> &amp;c. but alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that there are inſerted the Arms of the Principal Houſes or Families of <hi>France,</hi> of the Prinees, Dukes, Prelates, and other No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen of the Order of the Holy Ghoſt, together with thoſe of the Marſhals of <hi>France,</hi> of the Colonels and other Military Officers, as alſo thoſe of the Regiments that have been lately raiſed, and laſtly thoſe of the Preſidents of the Soveraign Courts. I ſhall add one Inſcription, worthy to be Printed in the next Edition of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits Book, and made upon the Building <hi>Verſailles.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hic fuit ante Chaos, dixiſti &amp; Regia Verbo,</l>
                  <l>Fit <hi>Ludovice</hi> tuo, ſic fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ta eſt machina Mundi.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Which may be properly Paraphraſed in <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>That the Eternal Word the World ſhould frame,</l>
                  <l>A Wonder 'twas, till <hi>Lewis</hi> did the ſame.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II. NOUVELLE BIBLIOTHEQUE DES AUTHEURS ECCLESIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIQUES,</hi> &amp;c. Or, a new Library of Eccle ſcaſtical Authors, containing the Hiſtory of their Lives, a Catalogue and Chronology of their Writings, and an Epitome of whatſoever is comprehended therein, together with divers Critical Reflections on their Style and Doctrine, as alſo an Account of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Editions of their Works. <hi>In five Volumes in Quarto, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the Hiſtory of the ſix firſt Ages of the Church Printed at</hi> Mons, <hi>and to be Sold in</hi> London <hi>by</hi> Abel Swall, <hi>and</hi> Timothy Child <hi>at the</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicorn <hi>in St.</hi> Pauls <hi>Church-yard. 1692. the 1.</hi> Vol. pag. <hi>342.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Work hath been every where ſo much talk'd of, and hath been generally ſo well eſteemed among the Learned, that although
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54947:7"/>this is only a ſecond Edition, and a large account hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given of the two firſt Volumes in the <hi>Bibliotheque <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſelle;</hi> nevertheleſs we are perſwaded that it will not be altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceptable to the ingenious of our own Nation, who perhaps have not ſeen it, or at leaſt have receiv'd but little information con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Subject and deſign thereof, to repreſent to them a more particular Character both of the Author and the Book.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> is a Profeſſor of Divinity in the College of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> who according to the Teſtimony of divers learned<note n="*" place="margin">Vide <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e.</hi> Preſ. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſl. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tter.</note> Men, and even that of his own Works, hath been for a long time addicted to the Study of Eccleſiaſtical Antiquity. And as he is a man of great Parts, and endued wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h a clear and ſound Judgment; it may be eaſily imagn'd, that by frequent reading, he hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd many things that are Contrary to the Doctrine and Practice of that Church wherein he hath been Educated. But in a Society which cannot endure to be Contradicted in the leaſt matter, and that hates even the very Name of Reformation, it was dangerous to Communicate his Diſcoveries to the World, at leaſt until ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable opportunity did enable him to uſe a greater Liberty. It is probable that as ſoon as the Controverſies between <hi>France,</hi> and the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> concerning the <hi>Regalia,</hi> and the nomination to great Benefices began to ariſe, Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> was incited to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh his Remarks, but obſerving judiciouſly that this cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt would not be ſoon appeas'd, under a Prince ſo jealous of his Honour and Right, as <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and a Pope ſo obſtinate as <hi>Innocent.</hi> XI. he judg'd it to be expedient to afford them longer time to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated one againſt another; to the end that he might be more ſecure, and might diſcourſe more freely and with greater weight concerning the matters.</p>
               <p>The event happen'd as the Author had foreſeen; for the Pope vindicated the perſecuted <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> either as being of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or deſigning by the Publick expreſſing of a Compaſſion that coſt him nothing, to ſtrengthen his party with the acce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion of ſo conſiderable a number of Learned Divines, and of he beſt Writers in <hi>France.</hi> Whereupon the King being incenſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d that his Holineſs ſhould attempt as it were to preſcribe Laws to him, and ſhould endeavour to withdraw his Subjects from their Allegiance to him, took other meaſures, and having Summon'd an Aſſembly of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54947:8"/>his Clergy,<note n="†" place="margin">In the Year <hi>1682.</hi>
                  </note> caus'd it to be declar'd therein,
<list>
                     <item>1. That the Pope hath no Authority directly or indirectly over the Temporalities of Kings.</item>
                     <item>2. That much leſs hath he any power to depoſe them.</item>
                     <item>3. That he is not infallible.</item>
                     <item>4. That he is inferiour to a Council.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>At that time the breach ſeem'd to be irreparable, and it was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally believ'd that a Patriarch would e're long preſide in <hi>France.</hi> It is true indeed, that the perſecution of the Proteſtants, whoſe entire De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction was then haſten'd, afforded but little hope of a Reformation to the moderate part of <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks. However, many of them that were willing to flatter themſelves with vain Expectations, gave it out, that none ought to be diſcourag'd by theſe rigorous Perſecutions; that the Court, not being ignorant of the commotions that a too much precipitated Reformation hath produced in other places, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to proceed therein by degrees; And that even on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they had very good grounds to aboliſh, the Exerciſe of the Reformed Religion; either to avoid a Schiſm like unto that which vexes yet <hi>England</hi> at this preſent; or inſenſibly to gain the conſent of the old Catholicks by the Converſation of the new.</p>
               <p>Upon the whole matter, this is ſufficient to induce us to believe, that the Court of <hi>France</hi> is not unwilling that their Divines ſhould take the Advantage of this Conjuncture obliquely to aſſault the Superſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> However, Father <hi>Simon,</hi> to vindicate himſelf, in regard that our Author had refuted<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>4.</hi> Diſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Prol. P. <hi>30.38.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9.</hi>
                  </note> his too preſumptuous Conjectures on the Pentateuch, hath written againſt him with much animoſity, accuſing him as one that had employed his Pen to revive <hi>Calviniſm</hi> that was ſo lately extirpated: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, all theſe loud Clamours produced no effect, ſerving only to promote the Sale of the Book; neither have they oblig'd Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> to blot out theſe paſſages that were offenſive to his Adverſary; but only to add certain Notes in this Second Edition to prove that <hi>Moſes</hi> really compoſed the Pentateuch. And the Author is ſo far from having been reprehended for bringing allegations in favour of the Proteſtants; that the Cenſors of Books have loaded him with extraordinary Commendations in the beginning of the ſecond Volume, which they conclude in theſe words; <hi>That not being able to determine whether the vaſt extent of his Learning, the Sagacity of his Judgment, or the continual ſolidity of his Reflections, ought moſt to be admin'd; they find themſelves oblig'd to declare, that that which would ſerve for the Commendation of many, is not ſufficient to diſcharge all the Obligations that they judge to be due to his ſingular merit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54947:8"/>A large Preface is prefixed to the firſt Volume, wherein the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor explains and juſtifies the Title that he hath given to his Book, gives an account of his Deſign and Method, and propounds cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Critical Rules to determine whether a Work be forg'd, or whether it really appertains to the Perſon to whom it is Attributed. This Preface is follow'd with a Preliminary Diſſertation concerning the Books of the Bible; in which he treats,
<list>
                     <item>1. Of the Authors of the Books of the Old Teſtament in general.</item>
                     <item>2. Of the Canonical and Apocryphal Writings.</item>
                  </list> And indeed the judgment of Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> on this Article is very Remarkable, ſeeing he is a <hi>Roman</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, for according to his opinion the Six laſt Chapters of the Book of <hi>Eſther</hi> are not extant in the Hebrew Text, but were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from divers places, and contain ſeveral pieces apparently Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by the <hi>Helleniſt Jews.</hi> St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> expreſly rejects the Book of <hi>Buruch,</hi> as not being included in the Canon of Sacred Writings, in his Preface to the Prophecy of <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> The Hiſtory of <hi>Tobit</hi> is likewiſe excluded, in all the Ancient Catalogues, from the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Canonical Writings, as well as that of <hi>Judith;</hi> In a word, Chriſtian Antiquity hath follow'd the Canon of the <hi>Jews</hi> as to the Books of the Old Teſtament; there are no others Cited in the New, and a great part of theſe are often alledged therein; More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the Primitive Catalogues of Canonical Books, compoſed by the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Eccleſiaſtical Authors, do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any others. In the <hi>Chronicon</hi> of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> the Books of the <hi>Maccabees</hi> are ſeparated from thoſe of the Holy Scriptures, and placed in the Rank of <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Africanus.</hi> The Books of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> are inſerted in the Ancient Catalogues among thoſe Writings that are eſteem'd to be very uſeful, but ſuch as are not Canonical. Nothing can be inferr'd to prove their being Divinely inſpir'd, from thoſe paſſages that are produc'd by the Fathers, in regard that <hi>Origen,</hi> St. <hi>Jerom</hi> and St. <hi>Hilary,</hi> by whom they are cited, reckon them among the Apocryphal Writings. Moreover, theſe Books were not admitted into the Canon of holy Scripture even in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great: Foraſmuch as this Pope ſpeaks to this effect:<note n="†" place="margin">Greg. <hi>Lib.</hi> 12. <hi>Moral.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>We do nothing that is unreaſonable in exhibiting the Teſtimony of Books that are not Canonical, ſince they were Publiſhed for the Edification of the Church.</hi> Many Eccleſiaſtical Writers, both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> reckon only 22 Canonical Books, annexing the Hiſtory of <hi>Ruth</hi> to that of <hi>Judges,</hi> and the Lamentations of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54947:9"/>his Prophecies, although they lived after the third Council of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> and after <hi>Innocent</hi> I. who is reported to have inſerted the <hi>Maccabees</hi> and other Apocryphal Books into the ſacred Canon; which ſhews (adds our Author) <hi>that theſe definitions were not follow'd by all Authors and by all the Churches, until this was at laſt entirely determin'd by the Deciſion of the Council of Trent.</hi> Inſomuch that theſe Eccleſiaſtical Aſſemblies partake of this general property with the others, that the Decrees of the later ſhould aboliſh all thoſe of the preceeding; or otherwiſe, it is but juſt that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which hath a power to make new Articles of Faith, ſhould like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be inveſted with that of cauſing the Books from whence they are taken to be eſteem'd as Canonical.</p>
               <p>In the third Article of this diſſertation, the Author gives us the Hiſtory of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Original, of the Tranſlation of the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint, and of other <hi>Greek</hi> Verſions of the Old Teſtament. 4. He diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſeth anfterwards concerning certain Authors, whoſe works have ſome Relation to the Sacred Writings of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> as <hi>Philo, Joſephus, Ariſtaeus,</hi> &amp;c. 5. He treats of the Authors of the Books of the New Teſtament. And 6. of the Canon of theſe Books.</p>
               <p>Let us now proceed to the Body of the Work. Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> hath thought ſit to reject the Liturgies<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 8.</note> that are attributed to the Apoſtles, <hi>in regard</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that we need only to reflect a little on what we Read in the firſt Epiſtle of St.</hi> Paul <hi>to the</hi> Corinthians, <hi>concerning the Celebration of the Euchariſt, and on that which hath been alledg'd on this Subject by St.</hi> Juſtin, <hi>and the Primitive Fathers of the Church, to be convinc'd that the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors celebrated the</hi> Sacrifice of the Maſs <hi>with great Simplicity. A very ſmall number of Litanies were, recited therein, but by little and little, ſome other Collects were added, together with certain exterior Ceremonies to render the Service more venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the People, laſtly the Churches proceeded to regulate and to commit theſe particular Methods to Writing; and this is that which we call Liturgies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Author is not only content to diſallow the Works of the Counterfeit St <hi>Denis,</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 24.</note> (<hi>b</hi>) but he likewiſe proves in one of his Notes,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 38.</note> that the true <hi>Dionyſius the Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>opagite</hi> never was in <hi>France;</hi> that <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi> firſt propagated the Chriſtian Religion in that Kingdom; and that in the time of St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> his Succeſſor, Chriſtianity was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhd only in that part of the Country call'd <hi>Gallia Viennenſis &amp; Lugdurenſis,</hi> ſince there were no Martyrs any where but within the Limits of theſe two Provinces; concerning whom he produceth<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 50.</note>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:54947:9"/>an Epiſtle of the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> to thoſe of <hi>Pontus,</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be remembred in more than one place. The Pagans having hindred the Chriſtians from carrying off the Body of <hi>Polycarp</hi> that remain'd entire in the midſt of the Flames, leſt (as was pretended by theſe deluded <hi>Heathens</hi>) they ſhould adore it inſtead of Jeſus Chriſt; the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> made this reflection thereupon, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>theſe People were poſſeſs'd with an extravagant frenzy, as being ignorant that the Chriſtians adore</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>only becauſe he is the Son of God, and that they honour the Martyrs, who are his Diſciples and followers, only on the account of the Love that they teſtifie for their King and Maſter.</hi> Afterward, <hi>The Centurion having caus'd the Body of this Martyr to be burnt, the Chriſtians took away his Bones, being more valuable than the moſt precious Stones, and more pure than Gold, which they</hi> BURIED <hi>in a place where they Aſſembled together, to Celebrate with joy and Chearfulneſs, the Day of his Martyrdom; thus</hi> HONOU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RING <hi>the</hi> MEMORY <hi>of thoſe that had fought Gloriouſly for their Religion, to the end that they might confirm and inſtruct others by ſuch Examples.</hi> Theſe are the Sentiments (adds our Author) of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church, concerning the Reſpect due to Martyrs and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, explain'd after a very clear and diſtinct manner, equidiſtant from the contempt that is caſt on them by our Modern Hereticks, and from the Superſtition of ſome Catholicks. But Mr. <hi>Du P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> would have extreamly oblig'd the World in ſhewing who thoſe Hereticks are, who deſpiſe the Holy Martyrs, and their true Relicks, and refuſe to afford them this ſort of honour that was done to their memory, by the Church of <hi>Smyrna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Edition is an extract of <hi>Origen</hi>'s Book concerning Prayer,<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 142.145.</note> which the Author had not ſeen when he publiſh'd the firſt; and on the occaſion of the diſpute that roſe between St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and the Biſhop, of <hi>Rome</hi> concerning the Repeating of Baptiſm, he produceth a remarkable paſſage<note n="(f)" place="margin">164 2.</note> taken from the Acts of the laſt Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> holden in the Year 256. Wherein this Father exhorting the 87 Biſhops that were there preſent, freely to diſcloſe their mind, without any deſign of excommunicating thoſe that were of a different opinion, gives them this reaſon. <hi>For none ought to Style himſelf Biſhop of Biſhops, to endeavour to conſtrain his Colleagues by a Tyrannical Authority, by reaſon that every Biſhop hath liberty, and power to make uſe thereof, as he ſhall think fit, and that he can no more be judg'd by another, than he can judge him: But we ought all to attend
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54947:10"/>to the judgment of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>who alone hath power to ſet us over his Church, and to judge of our Actions.</hi> In this Controverſy both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties pretended to have Tradition on their ſide, and St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to that which was alledg'd againſt him by Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> the truth of the Goſpel and the Primitive Tradition of the Apoſtles. The Edition of the Works of this Father, which is declar'd by Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> to be generally moſt eſteem'd, is that which hath been Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed ſome years ago by two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Biſhops, and Printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> but the Annotations of <hi>Pamelius</hi> are not much reguarded, by reaſon that he applies himſelf rather to confirm the Doctrine and diſcipline that is received and maintain'd by thoſe of his own Society, than to explain the difficulties that occur in the Text of the Author.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> doubts<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 199.1.</note> whether the paſſage recited by <hi>Joannes Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcenus,</hi> in his third Homily concerning Images, appertains to <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodius:</hi> it is declared therein that the Chriſtians made certain Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of Gold repreſenting the Angels, for the Glory of God; if it were written by this Biſhop, it muſt be taken (ſaid he) in another Sence, different from that which is attributed to it by <hi>Damaſcenus;</hi> and by theſe words, <hi>Angels, Principalities</hi> and <hi>Powers,</hi> the Kings of the Earth are to be underſtood, as may be inferr'd from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding expreſſions. Moreover he rejects all the Decretals that are imputed to the Primitive Popes, and believe that they were forg'd by <hi>Riculphus</hi> and his Succeſſor <hi>Benedict</hi> in the ninth Century. Laſtly, he concludes this Volume, with an Epitome of the Doctrine, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and Moral Inſtructions of the Church in the three firſt Ages thereof. There are no notes ſubjoined to this Abridgment, becauſe it is taken for granted, that ſufficient prooſs of all that is aſſerted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, have been already exhibited in the body of the Work: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, it cannot be diſcerned by what Arguments alledg'd in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Treatiſe, Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> ſupports the following Propoſitions that are afterward maintain'd by him in the ſaid Epitome; <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>(1) That altho' all the Fathers are not agreed, that Infants are born in Sin, and liable to Damnation, yet the contrary opinion was more agreeable to the Church.</item>
                     <item>(2) That the Sacrifice of the Maſs was Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated in Memory of the Dead.</item>
                     <item>(3) That the ancient Chriſtians invocated the Saints and Martyrs deceas'd; and that they were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that they prayed to God for the living.</item>
                  </list> However, there are other Principles that are grounded on better Authority, and ſuch as are of great importance with reſpect to the preſent differences
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54947:10"/>among Chriſtians.
<list>
                     <item>(1) That the ancient Writers always mention'd the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> with a great deal of reſpect, tho' they have not exceeded their due bounds, as it hath been afterwards practiſed; that it was not generally believed that ſhe remain'd a Virgin after her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery; that no mention hath been made of her aſſumption, and that there is a paſſage in the works of S. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> which is not favourable to the immaculate conception.</item>
                     <item>(2) That the Holy Scripture contains the principal Articles of our Faith, and that it was lawful for all Chriſtians to read it.</item>
                     <item>(3) That the Elements of the Euchariſt were ordinary Bread, and Wine, mingled with water; That the conſecrated Bread was divided into little pieces; that the Deacons diſtributed it to thoſe that were preſent who receiv'd it in their hands, and that they likewiſe gave them ſome of the conſecrated wine; That in ſome Churches this diſtribution was reſerved to the Prieſts, but that in others every one approached to the Table and took his Portion of the Euchariſt.</item>
                     <item>(4) That during the three firſt Centuries, there is no account concerning the unction or annointing of the ſick mentioned by St. <hi>James.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>(5) That the Clergy were forbidden to be engag'd in Civil and Temporal Affairs.</item>
                     <item>(6) That Prieſts were permitted to keep their Wives whom they had eſpouſed, before they were Ordained, and not to marry any after their Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but that both was allow'd to Deacons.</item>
                     <item>(7) That there have ſcarcely been any diſputes, or different ſentiments in the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Moral Duties.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>We find divers Tables at the end of this Work, ſome of which are Chronological, and ſhew the time of the Nativity, Death, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Tranſactions of the Sacred Writers, and Eccleſiaſtical Authors; others ſerve to diſtinguiſh the genuine Works from thoſe that are forg'd. There are alſo Alphabetical Indexes of the Authors and Principal matters.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> hath obſerved in the Second Volume the ſame Method as in the preceeding, all the difference is, that the Works of the Fathers of the fourth Century, being generally more known and in greater number than thoſe of the three firſt; there are likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted more frequent reflections on the Proteſtants, perhaps to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the importunate clamours of ſome Zealots, who otherwiſe would have ſuppreſſed the Book. However the ſame ſincerity and liberty of ſpeech which was ſo acceptable to all judicious Readers in the firſt Volume, is every where conſpicuous throughout the ſecond.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:54947:11"/>It is apparent from the Life of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> which is exhibited at large by our Author, that the People began even in his time to adhere too much to the exteriour part of Religion, ſince two of the greateſt Crimes with which the <hi>Arrians</hi> charg'd this Father were, that he had broken a Chalice, and had adminiſter'd the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a Church that was not Conſecrated. It may be alſo obſerv'd, after Mr. <hi>Du Pin,</hi> that Lay-men were then admitted to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in both kinds; that there were Women that kept their Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and were not ſhut up in Monaſteries; that there were married Prieſts and Biſhops; that the Monks might alter their condition, and take Wives; that it was not lawful to make new Articles of Faith; and that Councils, even the Oecumenical, were only the Witneſſes of the Creed of their Ages, whereas they had Soveraign Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to determine all matters that related to Diſcipline. Thus it is expreſly declar'd by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Biſhops, in appointing the day for the Celebration of the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter. It ſeems good to us, we think fit that it ſhould be ſo.</hi> But their Expreſſions are altogether diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent with reſpect to the Conſubſtantiality of the Word, ſince after having declar'd their Opinion as to this matter, they are content only to ſubjoyn; <hi>ſuch is the Faith of the Catholick Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Extracts of the Writings of the Fathers, we find thoſe of the Councils that were conven'd in the fourth Century. The Canons of that which is called the Council of <hi>Elvira,</hi> are an Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Code or Collection of the Councils of <hi>Spain,</hi> and it cannot be doubted but that they are very Authentick and of great Antiquity. The 34 and 36 Canons have cauſed much perplexity among the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Divines. One of them prohibits the lighting of Tapers in the Church-yards, by reaſon that the Spirits of the Saints ought not to be diſturbed: and the other to ſet up Pictures in the Churches, leſt the Object of our Adoration ſhould be Painted on the Walls. <hi>Many have endeavoured to render divers Explications of theſe Paſſages, but it ſeems to me,</hi> ſays Mr. <hi>Du Pin, to be more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to underſtand them ſimply, and to acknowledge that the Fathers of this Council did not approve the uſe of Images, no more than that of Wax-Candles lighted at Noon-day: but,</hi> continues he, <hi>theſe things are matters of Diſcipline, and may be obſerv'd or neglected without any prejudice to the Faith of the Church.</hi> The 35 Canon forbids Women to remain all night in the Church-yards, in regard that often under pretence of Prayer, they ſecretly committed abominable crimes. The 60 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54947:11"/>them of the quality of a Martyr, that are put to death for publickly demoliſhing of Idols, becauſe it is not enjoyned in the Goſpel, neither do we read that this was practiſed by the Chriſtians in the time of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>The ſame perverſe ſpirit that hath cauſed the Canons of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Elvira</hi> to be wreſted to a contrary ſenſe, hath in like manner given occaſion to ſome to doubt as to the truth of the Hiſtory of <hi>Paphnutius</hi> related by <hi>Socrates, Lib.</hi> I. <hi>Chap.</hi> XI. This <hi>Egyptian</hi> Biſhop oppos'd the new Law, that was intended to be enacted in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> to oblige the Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons to live ſingle, and to abſtain from their Wives, whom they had married before their Ordination. For although he himſelf was never married, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he maintain'd that this Yoak ought not to be laid on the Clergy, and that it was to expoſe the Chaſtity of Women to apparent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>I believe,</hi> (ſaid Mr. <hi>Du Pin,</hi> in ſpeaking to the <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctors) <hi>that this doubt proceeds rather from a fear with which ſome are poſſeſs'd, that this matter of Fact ſhould in any wiſe impugn the preſent Diſcipline, than from any ſolid Proof. But theſe Perſons ought to conſider, that this Ordinance is purely concerning Diſcipline, that the Diſcipline of the Church may be alter'd as opportunity ſerves, and that it is not neceſſary for the vindication thereof, to prove that it hath been always uniform in all Places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover our Author ſhews that <hi>Hoſins</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corduba</hi> preſided in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, and not the Popes Legats. He acknowledgeth as the authentick Records of this Synod, only the Form of Faith, the Epiſtle to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the Decree concerning the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and the firſt 20 Canons: And conſequently he rejects as ſuppoſitions Pieces, the <hi>Latin</hi> Letter of this Council to <hi>S. Sylveſter,</hi> together with the Anſwer of this Biſhop, and the Canons of a pretended Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod holden at <hi>Rome</hi> for the Confirmation of that of <hi>Nice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 59. as alſo the 60 and laſt Canon of the Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi> believes to have been convened between the years 360 and 370. It is prohibited to read in the Church any other Books than the Canonical, and thoſe only are acknowledged as ſuch, which are allow'd by the Proteſtants, excepting the Revelation.</p>
               <p>The 8. Canon of the Council of <hi>Saragoſſa</hi> forbids the vailing of Nuns before the age of 40 years.</p>
               <p>The Biſhops of <hi>Macedonia</hi> being about to confirm a Cenſure that they had made againſt a certain Biſhop named <hi>Bonoſius,</hi> and deſiring
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54947:12"/>the advice of Pope <hi>Siricius,</hi> he replied, <hi>That the Council of</hi> CAPUA, <hi>having referr'd this cauſe to them, it did not appertain to him to give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Judgment therein, and that they had power to determine it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt ancient Record (according to the opinion of Mr. <hi>Du Pin</hi>) in which the name of Maſs is applied to ſignifie the publick Prayers, recited by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in celebrating the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, is the third Canon of the II. Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> holden <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Domini</hi> 390.</p>
               <p>In the end of this Volume, the Author exhibits an Epitome of the Doctrine of the fourth Century, as he hath done in the preceeding, with reſpect to the firſt three, and he avoucheth that, altho' no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was taught in the fourth Age of the Church, but what was likewiſe believed in the three former; nevertheleſs the principal Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion have been much illuſtrated and explained therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Commentaries on Latin Authors. <hi>Q. HORATII FLACCI</hi> Poemata Interpretatione &amp; notis illuſtravit <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Rodellius</hi> é Soc. Jeſu, juſſu Chriſtianiſſimi Regis ad uſum Sereniſſ. Delphini, huic Editioni acceſſerunt Odae aliquot &amp; Satyrae: unà cum inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatione continuâ, quae in priori deſiderabantur, nec non Index re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Phraſium &amp; Verborum memorabilium. <hi>8.</hi> Lond. Impenſis Abel Swalle. <hi>1690. pag. 366.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Edition which is no leſs correct than that of <hi>Paris,</hi> hath moreover this advantage, that it contains the entire Works of <hi>Horace.</hi> Father <hi>Rodellius</hi> thought fit indeed not only to avoid the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of divers Odes and Satyrs, that ſeemed to him to be ſomewhat too luxuriant and offenſive to chaſt minds, but even wholly to retrench them, nevertheleſs this defect is now ſupplied, by reprinting theſe Pieces that were omitted, and by Paraphraſing all the reſt, excepting about half of the ſecond Satyr.</p>
               <p n="1">I. THE Author having perus'd Mr. <hi>Dacier</hi>'s Tranſlation and Critical Remarks, undertakes to cenſure ſome of thoſe that are not. agreeable to his opinion. The latter in his <hi>French</hi> Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on declares, that whereas <hi>Horace</hi> makes mention of <hi>Maecenas</hi> thus;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54947:12"/>
                  <hi>Atavis edite Regibus.</hi> Theſe words are not to be underſtood, as if <hi>Maecenas</hi> were really deſcended from the Kings of <hi>Etreria,</hi> ſince there is not ſo much as one Hiſtorian, that takes any notice of the Royal Stock of this Favourite of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> but they all affirm that he derived his extraction, from an illuſtrious Family of Knights. The ancient Commentators produce three Names of theſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Kings, but he avoucheth it to be a counterfeit Liſt, and that they were deceived in taking <hi>Atavus</hi> for a Great Grand-Father. As for his part, by the word <hi>Reges</hi> he underſtands, Noblemen, or Perſons of conſiderable Quality, inſomuch that according to his Judgment, the meaning of <hi>Horace</hi> was only this, that <hi>Maecenas</hi> was deſcended of an ancient Family of <hi>Etreria.</hi> It muſt be granted that the words <hi>Rex &amp; Regina</hi> are often uſed in that ſenſe which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by Mr. <hi>Dacier;</hi> but on the other hand, <hi>Rodellius</hi> inſiſts, that in this place the word <hi>Rex</hi> ought to be taken in its proper and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine ſignification, as well as in the following Verſe of <hi>Propertius.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Maecenas</hi> eques Etruſco de Sanguine Regum.</q>
               <p>The Hiſtorians might eaſily omit this circumſtance relating to the Noble Extraction of <hi>Maecenas,</hi> by reaſon that none of them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to give a particular account of his life, and it is mention'd by the Poets, in regard that they had receiv'd the greateſt ſhare of his favours. Neither indeed could <hi>Maecenas</hi> derive his Pedigree from the Kings of <hi>Etreria,</hi> but at a very great diſtance; ſo that according to the judgment of <hi>Rodellius,</hi> as well as that of Mr. <hi>Dacier,</hi> the name of <hi>Cecina</hi> that is attributed to the Great Grand-Father of this Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Perſon, and who is reputed to have been King of <hi>Etreria,</hi> is meerly feigned. Beſides the Kings of <hi>Etreria</hi> were not very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, if we may give credit to the Teſtimony of <hi>Dionyſius Hallicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſaeus, Lucius Florus,</hi> and other Ancient Writers. There were twelve in number at the ſame time, and altho' they had an Equipage like unto that of the <hi>Roman Conſuls,</hi> together with a Scepter and a Crown; nevertheleſs they reigned only within the narrow bounds of one City, as <hi>Porſenna</hi> at <hi>Cluſium.</hi> Therefore altho' it ought not to be accounted as a matter of no moment to be deſcended from thoſe Kings. Yet it is not of ſo great conſequence, as that it ſhould be admir'd that the Hiſtorians have not made mention thereof, with reſpect to <hi>Maecenas.</hi> Theſe are the reaſons alledged by <hi>Rodellius,</hi> which being confirmed by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54947:13"/>the Authority of <hi>Propertius,</hi> will without doubt cauſe many to incline to his Opinion.</p>
               <p>It is not ſufficient, that becauſe a word, as that of <hi>Rex,</hi> is uſed in a certain ſenſe in ſome places, therefore it ought to be explain'd after the ſame manner whereſoever it is poſſible that this ſignification may be admitted; it muſt alſo be attended with certain circumſtances which favour this ſenſe, and determin that equivocal word thereto. It is requiſite then to enquire whether it be probable that in the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Horace</hi> and <hi>Propertius</hi> the word <hi>Rex</hi> ſhould be taken for a Rich or Noble Man; but we ſhall leave this to the deciſion of thoſe that are expert Criticks in the Latin Tongue.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Father <hi>Rodellius</hi> hath annexed a Chronological Epitome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory from the 21. year of <hi>Horace</hi> to the 57. which account indeed is uſeful for the more clear underſtanding of the Works of this Poet; but the Chronology of <hi>Horace</hi>'s Odes inſerted in <hi>Tanaquil Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>'s Letters would not have been leſs advantageous; and <hi>Rodellius</hi> would not have acted more unjuſtly in borrowing from him all this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Work, and in doing him that juſtice which is due to his merits, than in taking only part of his deſign: for altho' <hi>Faber</hi> died among thoſe of the Reformed Religion, nevertheleſs there is no Jeſuit that can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him the reputation of a good Grammarian, which quality hath been always eſteemed to be conſiſtent with that of an ill <hi>Roman</hi>-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Moreover <hi>Rodellius</hi> contradicts M. <hi>Dacier</hi> with reſpect to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication publiſhed by the later on the 6 Verſe of the 1 Ode. <hi>Terrarum Dominos evehit ad Deos;</hi> which M. <hi>Dacier</hi> underſtands, not with reference to thoſe that are properly called Gods, but concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe that had obtain'd the prize in the Olympick Games, whom <hi>Horace</hi> elſe-where ſtiles <hi>Coeleſtes.</hi> The <hi>Latin</hi> Interpretation is conſonant to the ordinary acceptation of the words, that is to ſay, that they which overcame believ'd that they had acquired a great deal of Honour, which might be Hyperbolically termed <hi>a Glory equal to that of the Gods. Horace</hi> makes uſe of the ſame Figure twice in this <hi>Ode.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Me doctarum hederae praemia frontium,</l>
                     <l>Dis miſcent ſuperis.</l>
                  </q> And
<q>Sublimi feriam ſidera vertice.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It is likewiſe known that this expreſſion <hi>Deus eſſe,</hi> is commonly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54947:13"/>to ſignifie to be eſteemed happy; moreover the Epithet of <hi>Terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Domini</hi> entirely determines the ſenſe, and it may juſtly be admir'd that M. <hi>Dacier</hi> hath not obſerv'd it, ſince he hath ſo clearly explained divers paſſages that are far more difficult. It is true indeed that he is not the firſt Interpreter, who through a commendable emulation and earneſt endeavour to offer ſomewhat that is new, and to excel o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, hath been induc'd to deviate from his Authors meaning, and to ſeek for too many Myſteries therein. We are ſometimes apt to loſe our Subject by too intenſe an application of the mind, and by how much the greater our efforts are, ſo much the farther we depart from the true ſenſe, to which it is afterwards very difficult to return. On the other ſide, if we do not apply our ſelves with a great deal of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to the reading of an Author, either we underſtand not what he ſays, or we let ſlip very conſiderable difficulties, without illuſtrating them. To be ſucceſsful, we muſt take care to keep the middle path between theſe two extremities, but this precept is more eaſily given to others than followed by themſelves. However it may be obſerv'd much better than it is generally done, if we could be perſwaded to remain in ſuſpenſe for a while, as touching the meaning of thoſe paſſages, wherein we ſuſpect that others have been deceived, and in the mean time if it be poſſible often to read over that Paragraph concerning which we are doubtful. But as ſoon as a new explication comes into our mind, if it have never ſo little ſhew of probability, we are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately reſtleſs and impatient, till we have committed it to Writing; and when it is once written, we find it to be extreamly difficult to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face or revoke it.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. TANAQUIL <hi>Faber</hi> had endeavour'd to ſhew in his Epiſtles, that the 14. <hi>Ode</hi> of the <hi>1ſt.</hi> Book ought to be underſtood literally; where it was generally believ'd that <hi>Horace</hi> deſigned to repreſent the State of the <hi>Roman</hi> Common-wealth that was ready to be engaged in a new Civil War after the defeat of <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius,</hi> under the <hi>Idea</hi> of a diſabled Veſſel that was again to be expos'd to the tempeſtuous waves. He affirmed that there was nothing Allegorical in this Ode, but that the Poet addreſs'd himſelf to the Ship that had convey'd him from <hi>Philippi</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> and that was about to return by the ſame way, with thoſe that had accompanied him in this Voyage. Father <hi>Rodellius</hi> who ſeems to fear leſt there ſhould be ſomething of danger in oppoſing the Torrent of Interpreters, as his Divines aver, that it is not lawful to depart from the general conſent of the Doctors, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54947:14"/>the contrary opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is an Allegory in this place. They that are deſirous to be further informed in this matter, may at their leiſure compare his aſſertions with the reaſons that are alledged by <hi>Tan. Faber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. THERE is a paſſage in the 2d. <hi>Ode</hi> of the 2d. Book, which hath very much perplex'd Interpreters, and it is this,
<q>
                     <l>Quiſquis ingentes occulo irretortor.</l>
                     <l>Spectat acervos.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Dacier</hi> explains this Phraſe <hi>Occulo irretorto, with a ſtreight</hi> or direct <hi>Eye;</hi> that is to ſay, without envy; for the property of envy is to look askew; and <hi>Rodellius</hi> inſiſts that this is the Character of a man of whom it may be ſaid, <hi>That the brightneſs of Gold does not at all dazle his Eyes, and he is never blinded thereby.</hi> This indeed comprehends the ſenſe in general, and ſeveral Commentators have obſerv'd it before them, as may be ſeen in an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Edition of <hi>Horace</hi>'s Works, together with the Annotations of 40 Grammarians, Printed at <hi>Baſil</hi> in the year 1580 in <hi>Fol.</hi> But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out injuring the reputation of thoſe Gentlemen, it may be juſtly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, or that they have not ſufficiently expreſs'd the ſence of the word <hi>irretorto. Torquere oculos</hi> ſignifies to turn our eyes to a certain place.</p>
               <q>—Oculoſque ad maenia torſit.</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Retorquere oculos,</hi> is to turn the head backwards to look on ſomething that we have left behind us; thus <hi>Cicero,</hi> in his ſecond Oration againſt <hi>Catilina,</hi> which he made after he had compel'd that Traytor to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence he departed with great indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Retorquet oculos profecto ſaepe ad hanc <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbem, quam ex ſuis faucibus ereptam eſſe luget. He often turns his head to view this City, and grows deſperate, by reaſon that his attempts againſt it have failed.</hi> It may be ſaid of a man that leaves his Native Country without expreſſing any ſorrow: <hi>Spectavit maenia patriae exiens oculo irretorto,</hi> or, <hi>egreſſus maenibus non retorſit oculos. Horace</hi> repreſents a man that deſpiſeth Riches after the ſame manner, as it were, paſſing through vaſt Mountains of Gold, but beholding them only whilſt they are before him, without vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafing to look back on them when he is paſt, which ſhews that he doth not regard them; for we are accuſtomed to turn our heads, that we may retain thoſe things longer in our ſight; which we are conſtrain'd to leave with much regret.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54947:14"/>VI. IN regard that it hath been obſerv'd by thoſe that have ſeen this Edition of <hi>Rodellius,</hi> that he therein often oppoſeth the judgment of M. <hi>Dacier,</hi> it might be expected that he ſhould have made ſome Critical Remarks on a paſſage in his Notes on the 21 Ode of the 3d. Book but he hath taken no notice thereof. <hi>Horace</hi> addreſſing himſelf to a certain Bottle or Pitcher, hath this expreſſion,
<q>
                     <l>Deſcende <hi>Corvino</hi> jubente</l>
                     <l>Promere languidiora Vina.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Go down, ſince</hi> Corvinus <hi>hath commanded me to entertain him with the moſt delicate Wine.</hi> M. <hi>Dacier</hi> obſerves on the word <hi>deſcende,</hi> that the <hi>Romans kept their Wines in Ware-Houſes built on the top of their Houſes, that they might be ripened with the Smoak.</hi> He would have done well, if he had quoted his Authors; for none can imagine that Wine above twenty years old at leaſt, ſuch as that which is here mentioned being as old as <hi>Horace,</hi> ſhould be kept in a Garret to ripen it with the Smoak. This perhaps might have been a good method to make Vinegar thereof, but by no means to render it more delicate. He might then have affirmed, on much better grounds, that the <hi>Romans</hi> uſually hung their Bottels on the walls of their Cellars, as may be inferr'd from the 23. and 24. Chapters of <hi>Cato</hi>'s Treatiſe <hi>de re Ruſtica.</hi> This is one of thoſe things which it were to be wiſhed that M. <hi>Dacier</hi> had always obſerved, at leaſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his Authors, when he exhibits any remarkable circumſtance or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion; for we live in an Age that is extreamly diſtruſtful, by reaſon that divers Criticks have been known to avouch thoſe things whereof they could alledge no proof, with no leſs aſſurance than thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which there is the greateſt Evidence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV. LES COMEDIES DE TERENCE traduites en François par Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame D'ACIER,</hi> &amp;c. The Comedies of <hi>TERENTIUS,</hi> Tranſlated into <hi>French</hi> by Madam <hi>D'Acier,</hi> with ſome remarks upon them. The laſt Edition Corrected and enrich'd with Figures at the head of each
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54947:15"/>Comedy. <hi>12.</hi> Divided into three Parts. The I. hath <hi>576</hi> pag. The II. <hi>490.</hi> The III. <hi>432.</hi> Printed in <hi>Amſterdam 1691</hi> for the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Huguetan,</hi> and are to be Sold in <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Abel Swalle</hi> and <hi>Tim. Child.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This Edition is Printed after the ſame manner, and even Page for Page according to that of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. WE find in a large Preface prefix'd at the beginning of the 1. Tome a Compariſon between <hi>Plantus</hi> and <hi>Terence,</hi> the ſubſtance whereof is this, that <hi>Plautus</hi> had more vigour than <hi>Terence,</hi> that he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in the vivacity of Action, and in the contriving of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues, that he ſhewed more skill in acting than in ſpeaking; but that his Sentences were often too much affected, his Drolleries groſs, and his Style ſometimes low: Whereas <hi>Terence</hi> is not ſo accurate in his deſigns, and excels rather in ſpeaking than acting; but his Style is far more correct, his Morals better diſpos'd, and his Drolleries much more refin'd; And it is for this reaſon that the ingenious take more delight in peruſing <hi>Terence</hi>'s Comedies, than in reading thoſe of <hi>Plautus,</hi> and on the contrary the common People prefer the later before the former; and it is on this account likewiſe, that altho' other Poets are more eſteem'd than <hi>Terence,</hi> nevertheleſs, he is reckon'd among thoſe of the firſt Rank, with reſpect to the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of manners. Upon the whole matter, as when we happen to light upon a thought or conception that we judge to be appoſite, and which we are deſirous to preſerve, we are ſo much accuſtomed to act a certain part, that when we would repreſent another, we cannot forbear intermixing with it ſomewhat of this Air, wherein we have been confirm'd by a continual habit: thus that ingenious diſpoſition of mind which <hi>Terence</hi> might participate with <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> is more or leſs conſpicuous in all the Perſonages that he brings on the Stage; we cannot diſcover any thing that is outragious or irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar therein, neither do we find thoſe mean and ſordid expreſſions that are uſed by the vulgar. To prove this, we need only to compare the diſcourſes of <hi>Thraſo</hi> and <hi>Gnatho,</hi> with thoſe of the <hi>Miles glorioſus</hi> and the Paraſites that are introduc'd by <hi>Plautus;</hi> the later indeed was skilful in cauſing the multitude to ſhout, but <hi>Terence</hi> afforded ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the judicious Auditory, who do not make their divertiſement to conſiſt in the obſtreporous noiſe of Laughter, to which the Rabble is addicted, but in hearing ſomewhat recited that ſavours of real wit and ingenuity.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:54947:15"/>II. MOREOVER Madam <hi>D'Acier</hi> vindicates her deſign in tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the entire Works of <hi>Terence,</hi> foreſeeing that ſome Criticks might be ſo ſcrupulous as to diſlike what ſhe hath done, by reaſon <hi>that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain pious and worthy Perſon ſeems to have believed that they ought not to be tranſlated without making great alterations, and very conſiderable additions.</hi> The ſame Gentleman publiſhed three Comedies in <hi>French,</hi> many years ago, which were received with great applauſe. They that are deſirous to know whether he hath as faithfully rendred the Author's ſenſe, as he hath taken care to repreſent it in an elegant ſtile, may compare his Verſion with that of Madam <hi>D'Acier,</hi> and I doubt not but that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a careful review of both, they will acknowledge that the latter hath better expreſs'd the genuine ſenſe and energy of the Original, which ſhe hath follow'd with much more exactneſs:</p>
               <p n="3">III. AFTERWARDS Madam <hi>D'Acier</hi> proceeds to entertain us with an account of the ſeveral Tranſlators and Interpreters of <hi>Terence</hi>'s Works, and more eſpecially of certain Figures that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted at the beginning of every Act, in two Manuſcripts of the <hi>French</hi> Kings Library, and which may contribute much to the more clear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of divers paſſages of this Author; but it were to be wiſhed that ſhe had caus'd them all to be well grav'd. Moreover ſhe hath found in theſe Manuſcripts the confirmation of certain conjectures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the order of ſome of the Scenes, that are generally attributed to thoſe Acts to which they do not appertain. Inſtead of annexing ſeparate examinations according to the Rules of Dramatick Poetry, as ſhe hath formerly done with reſpect to <hi>Plaurus,</hi> ſhe hath intermixed with her Remarks ſeveral particular obſervations relating to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Theatre, wherein ſhe gives an account of the alteration that ſhe has made in <hi>Terence,</hi> as to the diviſion of the Scenes and Acts. She admires <hi>that thoſe Comedies that have been in the poſſeſſion of learned Men for ſo many Ages, ſhould nevertheleſs remain even at this day in ſo great confuſion, that there are ſome Acts that commence where they ought not; that is to ſay, before the Theatre is clear'd:</hi> and ſhe <hi>declares that ſhe hath remedied this diſorder.</hi> The cauſe of this inadvertency is, that the greateſt part of Grammarians adhere much more to the words than to the matter, and imagine that they have ſufficiently explained the meaning of an Author, by ſhewing what every word hath been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſignifie ſeparately.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. AFTER the Preface we find a Tranſlation of <hi>Terence</hi>'s Life, Written by <hi>Suetonius,</hi> together with Obſervations, wherein all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54947:16"/>the obſcure paſſages thereof are illuſtrated, and divers Sentiments of the Ancients confirmed. She likewiſe gives us this judgment concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſix pieces of <hi>Terence</hi> that are now extant: The <hi>Andria</hi> and <hi>Adelphi</hi> ſeem to excel in the beauty of the Characters, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of manners; The <hi>Eunuchus</hi> and <hi>Phormio</hi> in the vivacity of the intrigues; And the <hi>Heautontimorumenos</hi> and <hi>Hecyra</hi> ſeem to have the pre-eminence, with reſpect to the excellency of the conceptions, and variety of paſſions, as alſo the purity and ſimplicity of the ſtile.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Laſtly, to exhibit a general <hi>Idea</hi> of this work, we ſhall here produce two paſſages in the Prologue of the <hi>Andria,</hi> one whereof is interpreted by Madam <hi>D'Acier</hi> after a new manner, and the other ſeems to require a little correction. <hi>Terence</hi>'s Enemies objected to him that he did ill in not ſimply tranſlating the Comedies of the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> into <hi>Latin,</hi> but in preſuming to compoſe a ſingle one in <hi>Latin,</hi> from many <hi>Greek;</hi> they expreſs'd their reſentment in theſe words: <hi>Contaminare non decere fabulas;</hi> which Madam <hi>D'Acier</hi> tranſlates, <hi>that it is not lawful to intermingle Comedies:</hi> She derives the word <hi>contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare</hi> from <hi>contango,</hi> affirming that it only ſignifies here to <hi>intermix,</hi> and that it is taken in a good ſenſe, inſomuch that when <hi>Terence</hi>'s Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries maintain'd that <hi>contaminare non decet fabulas,</hi> this Poet avouch'd that <hi>decet contaminare.</hi> This Etymology ſeems indeed to be true, and it is on this Account that <hi>contamino</hi> ſignifies <hi>to ſullie or pollute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing with touching it,</hi> according to <hi>Donatus</hi>'s remark; but we have no example, from which it may be evinc'd that this word was ever taken in a good ſenſe. <hi>Terence,</hi> after he hath produc'd the accuſation of his Enemies, in the ſame odious terms as they had exhibited it, doth not reply <hi>decet contaminare fabulas,</hi> but ſimply proves that it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to do that which they call'd <hi>contaminare.</hi> They pretended that <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence defil'd</hi> (if we may uſe the expreſſion) <hi>Menander</hi>'s Plays, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them ſomewhat of his own, or by annexing certain paſſages taken from other pieces of the ſame Poet, which being tranſpos'd, loſt a great part of their Primitive Beauty and Elegancy. Therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' Madam <hi>D'Acier,</hi> as to the main point, is of the ſame opinion as the other Interpreters; nevertheleſs every one will not admit that ſignification, which ſhe aſcribes unto the word <hi>contaminare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other paſſage of the Prologue to the <hi>Andria,</hi> which ſeems to ſtand in need of a ſmall alteration, is this,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54947:16"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Favete, adeſte aequo animo &amp; rem cognoſcite,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t pernoſcatis ecquid ſpei ſit reliquum,</l>
                     <l>Poſt haec quas faciet de integro Comedias,</l>
                     <l>Spectandae, an exigendae ſint vobis prius.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Give attention favourably, and examine this Piece, that you may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to judge what may be expected from our Poet, and whether the Comedies which he ſhall hereafter make, may deſerve to be acted before you, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ought to be rejected without hearing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let judicious Criticks determine whether this correction, which conſiſts in reading <hi>pernoſcat is</hi> in two words, be not more conſonant to the words and deſign of the Poet. <hi>Give attention favourably, &amp;c. To the end that he may know whether there be any grounds for him to hope for the future, and whether you will vouchſafe to grant that the new Comedies which he may hereafter compoſe, ſhall be acted, or whether you will explode them without ſeeing.</hi> At leaſt this ſenſe is more agreeable to theſe words, <hi>Ecquid ſpei ſit reliquum,</hi> &amp;c. Which after whatſoever manner they are underſtood, may be much better attributed to <hi>Terence</hi> than to the People of <hi>Rome.</hi> Perhaps this Comedy was acted after the <hi>Hecyra,</hi> or ſome other Play of this Poet was rejected, which caus'd him to fear leſt the like accident ſhould again happen. As for the People of <hi>Rome,</hi> they had no reaſon to deſpair of the ſufficiency of <hi>Terence</hi>'s Pieces, which they had already often approv'd; but the Poet having once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd a repulſe, might ſuſpect leſt this ſhould have done ſome injury to his credit, and ſhould occaſion the loſs of the publick approbation. The word <hi>reliquum</hi> joyn'd with <hi>ſpes</hi> ſeems altogether to favour this ſenſe, and is contrary to that of Madam <hi>D'Acier,</hi> who by <hi>ſpes</hi> underſtands <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectatio.</hi> Moreover it is a frequent cuſtom of <hi>Terence</hi> to make uſe of the Pronoun <hi>is</hi> inſtead of <hi>ille, hic, ipſe,</hi> as appears from the examples pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd by <hi>Robert Stephen</hi> in his <hi>Theſaurus linguae Latinae.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>V. CORNELIUS NEPOS</hi> de vita Excellentium Imperatorum; Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one &amp; notis illuſtravit <hi>NICOLAUS COURTIN,</hi> Humanitatis Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitate Pariſienſi. Juſſu Chriſtianiſſimi Regis, in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54947:17"/>Sereniſſimi Delphini, juxta Editionem Pariſienſem. <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Londini a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Abel Swalle. 1691. p. 264.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THo' <hi>Cornelius Nepos</hi> appears to be a very plain Author, and eaſie to be underſtood; he is ſo ſuccinct, and gives us the knowledge of ſo many Events and Antiquities, that the publick is without queſtion oblig'd to thoſe who took care of the Education of the Dauphin of <hi>France,</hi> and appointed a perſon of ſo much learning and judgement as Monſieur <hi>Courtin,</hi> to unfold the knotty difficulties of this Author. He has not given himſelf the trouble to make an unprofitable Paraphraſe upon this Hiſtorian. He has only explain'd his moſt extraordinary I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioms of Speech by the more common Phraſes; and tho' his Notes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear not very long, however they leave no difficulty in this Author un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>explained.</p>
               <p>Now in regard the Ancients are no very exact Chronologers, Mr. <hi>Courtin</hi> has plac'd before his Commentary a Chronology of 44 Olympi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ads, or 176 years. Which ſpace of time includes all the lives which <hi>Cornelius Nepos</hi> has written; and his Interpreter has taken care to mark out to what year the ſeveral Hiſtorical Actions therein recounted, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly refer. This Chronology begins from the 72. Olympiad, that is to ſay, according to his accompt, from the year of the World 3480. and the 261 year after the building of the City of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the lives of <hi>Cornelius Nepos</hi> Mr. <hi>Courtin</hi> has added all the Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that Author, which are extant, upon which he has alſo made Notes. At the end there is an Index of all the words of that Hiſtorian, conformable to the method of other Commentaries, for the uſe of the Dauphin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> D. <hi>JUNII JUVENALIS,</hi> &amp; <hi>A PERSIS FLACCI</hi> Satyrae, Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione &amp; notis illuſtravit <hi>LUDOVICUS PRATEUS,</hi> Rhetoricae Preceptor emeritus. Juſſu Chriſtianiſſimi Regis, in uſum Sereniſſimi Delphini, <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Lond. apud Abel Swalle, 1691. p. 606.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOnſieur PRATEUS has tranſlated theſe two Poets into other Latin, with ſo nice an exactneſs, as if he had ſtudied for a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Bible. For as he is oblig'd to add words to the Text, to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54947:17"/>make the conſtruction and contexture of the diſcourſe, he has taken care to mark them in other Letters. You will ſay perhaps that if he had made a freer Paraphraſe, he might have better explain'd his Authors; but he might as well have run himſelf into a miſtake of ſenſe. So that there is no queſtion but there are many people who will commend him for having been a little preciſe, eſpecially when they ſhall ſee that he has ſupply'd with ample Notes, what might be wanting to compleat the perſpicuity of the Paraphraſe. And indeed how was it poſſible to tranſlate clearly and in few words thoſe verſes of the 4 Satyr of <hi>Perſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Eſto;</l>
                  <l>Dum ndetcrius ſapiat Pannucia Baucis,</l>
                  <l>Cum bene diſcincto cantaverit Ocima vernae.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ocimum</hi> is an Aromatick Herb, which they never ſow'd but with Curſes and Maledictions, believing it would grow the better. <hi>Baucis</hi> was the name of a poor old Woman, and proverbially taken for any old Herb-woman. <hi>Socrates,</hi> who in this Satyr repreſents the perſon of <hi>Perſius,</hi> tells <hi>Alcibiades</hi> repreſenting the perſon of <hi>Nero,</hi> that tho' he might have reaſon to boaſt of the Nobility of his Extraction, and the Comlineſs of his Perſon; yet for all that, he might have no leſs cauſe to fear his being reproach'd, for having no more wit than a Herring-wife that abuſes a Footman. This is the Interpretation and meaning which, next to <hi>Caſaubon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prateus</hi> gives of this paſſage in <hi>Perſius.</hi> You ſhall find in his Notes all that the moſt ſubtle Criticks have ſaid to render <hi>Perſius</hi> intelligible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>VII. A DEFENCE OF <hi>DIOCESAN</hi> EPISCOPACY, <hi>in anſwer to a Book of Mr.</hi> David Clarkſon <hi>lately Publiſhed, Entituled Primitive E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy; by</hi> HEN. MAURICE D.D. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. London 1691. p. 470.</head>
               <p>IF all Books were written like this, I do not believe, there is any Mortal would be ſo adventurous as to undertake to be a Journaliſt; for there is neither Table of the Chapters nor of the Matters; nor any Titles upon the Chapters; nor is the deſign of the Author to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, either in the Preface or Introduction. So that a man muſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54947:18"/>have read the Book which the Author refutes, and know what it treats of, if he intends to make any advantage by the reading of this.</p>
               <p>That want of order might offend the Reader, and hinder the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Book, and yet neither Dr. <hi>Maurice</hi> nor his Bookſeller have any reaſon to complain. But this Book is otherwiſe ſo well written, and contains ſo many learned Obſervations, that 'tis great pity it ſhould not be as well known as it deſerves. And therefore we ſhall in a few words give you an account of what it treats. Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi> was a Non-Conformiſt, of the number of thoſe who are call'd Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, or <hi>Congregational</hi> Men, becauſe they believe that every Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is a Church <hi>apart,</hi> or a Society of Men by themſelves, over which no other has any thing to do; ſo that the Miniſter they have made choice of, is very near as Soveraign as the Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> or to make uſe of a Phraſe which leſs offends thoſe Gentlemen, as a Biſhop in his Dioceſs.</p>
               <p>To prove that this opinion is not ſo new as it ſeems at firſt, Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi> wrote a Book, entituled <hi>Primitive Epiſcopacy,</hi> which was not Publiſhed till after his deceaſe. The principal thing which he drives at, is to prove, that during the three firſt Ages, no Biſhop had above one Flock under his charge, that is to ſay, ſo many Chriſtians as the Place could contain wherein they aſſembled.</p>
               <p>To make this out, he endeavours to ſhew,
<list>
                     <item>1. That in the firſt Age there were none but Jews and Proſelytes that embrac'd the Chriſtian Religion, and thoſe but few in number.</item>
                     <item>2. That the Pagans that were converted in the ſecond and third Age were inconſiderable in reſpect of the Jews and other Pagans.</item>
                     <item>3. That there was a Biſhop almoſt in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Village.</item>
                     <item>4. That the greateſt part of the Cities were no bigger than the Villages and Borough Towns of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. That ſuch as were bigger were but thinly peopled; at leaſt that it is certain there were but very few Chriſtians in 'em.</item>
                     <item>6. That it ought to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Chriſtians were divided into ſeveral Sects, which had every one their particular Biſhops or Paſtors.</item>
                  </list> Dr. <hi>Maurice</hi> refutes theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections with a great deal more pains and Learning than they deſerve, in the ſix Chapters of which the whole Treatiſe conſiſts. But theſe anſwers would engage us in a too long diſcuſſion; beſides that we are convinc'd that the greateſt part of thoſe that will read this Journal, are almoſt able to diſcover the weakneſs of Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi>'s Arguments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:54947:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> An Accurate Deſcription of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and of the moſt conſiderable Parts of <hi>Germany, Swedeland,</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſuccinct accompt of what is moſt remarkable in theſe Countries; and neceſſary Inſtructions for Travellers; together with an exact relation of the Entertainment of his moſt Sacred Majeſty, K. <hi>WILLIAM</hi> at the <hi>Hague.</hi> Written by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman. <hi>8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. London</hi> for <hi>Tim. Child. 1691. p. 192.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRavels are always full of divertiſement, provided they be well written, but they are not always equally beneficial; for that they who do no more than ſlip into a Country, or make but a ſhort ſtay therein, can never thoroughly inform themſelves of the manners and cuſtoms of the people, or of the form of their Government, which is the principal thing to be inquir'd into. Therefore the Remarks of Sir <hi>William Temple</hi> are admir'd for ſo much as they give an account of ſuch things. The Author of this deſcription ſeems to have judgment enough to have been able to do the ſame, eſpecially having liv'd ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years in the Countries of which he ſpeaks. But it ſeems that he has avoided tracing the Footſteps of that learned Polititian; and that he has only applied himſelf to make remarks more profitable for Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers only, and more proper for the common ſort of People. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that you ſhall here find the deſcriptions of the moſt famous Cities of <hi>Holland, Germany, Sweeden,</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> of their ſcituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their Building, the Charges of travelling thither, and living there; beſides ſeveral Remarks upon their Trade, their Riches, the Inclinations of the Inhabitants, and which way to converſe with 'em, and win their Friendſhip. In the Obſervations which he makes upon theſe things he ſeems ſtill to have had in view the good of his Nation, and to incline thoſe that ſit at the Helm to reform certain abuſes, which if remov'd, the Nation would be in a more flouriſhing condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. You ſhall there find one example in the extract of a Letter of a Merchant who preferr'd living at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> before living in <hi>London,</hi> for reaſons very requiſite to be read<note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.113.</note> in the Author himſelf.</p>
               <p>To render his admonitions grateful to his fellow Countrymen, he ends with a diſcourſe very curious, and much to their advantage. He gives you a Catalogue of the 18 Cities of <hi>Holland</hi> that have voices in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54947:19"/>States of that Province; of 53 the moſt famous Cities of <hi>Germany</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries;</hi> of 22 of <hi>France;</hi> of 14 in <hi>Italy;</hi> beſides ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Territories of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Cantons of <hi>Switzerland.</hi> He ſets down the number of their Houſes, which he ſays he had out of the publick Regiſters, and comparing them afterwards with the Houſes in <hi>London,</hi> which he demonſtrates to be above 100000, he makes it out by that Calculation, that all the Cities of the Province of <hi>Holland</hi> joyned together do not contain ſo many Houſes as <hi>London</hi> and the Suburds, not having above 88909. That the 53 Cities of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> do not exceed the Capital City of <hi>England</hi> above a little more than two thirds; and that the 22 Cities of <hi>France</hi> have not once as many.</p>
               <p>The Relation of the King of <hi>England</hi>'s firſt Voyage into <hi>Holland</hi> is worth reading, eſpecially for perſons of Wit, who will there meet with very ingenious Deviſes and Inſcriptions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> The new Method of Fortification as practiſed by Monſieur <hi>Vauban</hi> Engineer General of <hi>France. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. London</hi> for <hi>Abel Swalle. 1691.</hi> p. <hi>183.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THo' this Book has been publiſhed by the Chevalier <hi>de Cambray,</hi> one of Mr. <hi>Vauban</hi>'s Pupils, it is certainly the work of that great Engineer, who compoſed it for the benefit of certain young Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and <hi>Cadets</hi> reſiding in divers Cities within the Dominions of the <hi>French</hi> King. To the end that they might be able to avoid the pains and trouble of reading over ſo many Voluminous Books that are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the <hi>German</hi> and other Languages on this Subject; the Author of this Tract hath taken care to epitomize all that he judged to be neceſſary for the attaining to perfection in this Art. And indeed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a large Treatiſe of practical Geometry prefixed at the beginning; the ſeveral Methods of almoſt all the Eminent Engineers that have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to appear'd in the World, are therein plainly exhibited; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that with a little obſervation we may be informed of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Fortifying of Places uſed by the <hi>Hollanders, Germans, Italians,</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> as well as moſt other Nations. Therefore in regard that this Book hath been generally well approv'd, the Publiſher of this <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſion could no longer refrain from imparting ſo valuable a treaſure
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54947:19"/>to his own Countrymen, that they might likewiſe reap the ſame ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereby, and it is on this account that he hath taken care that it ſhould even exceed the Original, by the means of ſeveral conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable alterations and amendments that are made in the tranſlation. Moreover, if curious and well-grav'd figures add any value to a Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Book, it may be juſtly expected that the great number of Cuts and accurate Schemes inſerted therein ſhould render it yet more acceptable.</p>
               <p>There are two parts in this Volume, one is a Treatiſe of practical Geometry, and the other a diſcourſe of Fortification; the Treatiſe of Geometry is likewiſe divided into two Books, in the firſt whereof are contained four Chapters, and in the ſecond ſix; in the former are exhibited the<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 6.</note> explication of the Terms of Geometry, and the<note n="(b)" place="margin">6.</note> operation of divers Problemes that may be drawn on Paper by way of recreation, with the help of a pair of Compaſſes and a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; together with the<note n="(c)" place="margin">22.</note> conſtruction of five regular bodies, and of many others that come near them, as alſo the<note n="(d)" place="margin">29.</note> manner of forming Piramids which ſhall have regular Polygons for their <hi>Baſes,</hi> from the Triangle to the Dodecagon. The ſecond Book comprehends the menſuration of<note n="(e)" place="margin">3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Heights, (the Authors Inſtrument for this purpoſe is the <hi>Aſtrolabe</hi>)<note n="(f)" place="margin">43.</note> Lengths,<note n="(g)" place="margin">62.</note> Plains,<note n="(h)" place="margin">6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Solids,<note n="(i)" place="margin">6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and Concaves, that is to ſay, according to his definition, the Art of meaſuring hollow bodies, to know how much they contain. Laſtly the method<note n="(k)" place="margin">74.</note> of making a body of a certain Figure equal to another of another Figure is therein taught which Art is call'd the tranſmutation of bodies, in oppoſition to that of ſurfaces repreſented in the ſecond Chapter of the firſt Book. This Treatiſe is concluded with a perſwaſion that what hath been therein deliver'd is ſufficient for thoſe that are deſirous to make a conſiderable Progreſs in the Art of Military Architecture.</p>
               <p>The Treatiſe of Fortification is divided into five Books, every one of which contains many Chapters: In the<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 1.</note> firſt whereof is explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the definition of Fortification, together with its Original and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts, as alſo the terms that are made uſe of in the attacking and defending of places. As for its Original, the Author affirms<note n="(m)" place="margin">3.</note> that at firſt the Aſſaults of Robbers and wild Beaſts being only feared, the People were content to ſatisfie themſelves with Hedges alone, which cuſtom continued even among ſome Nation 328 Years before our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Nativity. But in proceſs of time, the ambition of ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, who endeavoured to rule and tyrannize over their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, thoſe that deſired to enjoy their liberty, were obliged to dig
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54947:20"/>Trenches and build Walls, which they afterwards flanked with Towers, to the end that they might more eaſily repel the Enemy, when he ſhould happen to be lodg'd at the foot of the Wall to batter or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine it. At laſt a Monk of the Order of St. <hi>Francis</hi> named <hi>Berthold Schwartz</hi> of the City of <hi>Fribourg</hi> in the Country of <hi>Briſgan,</hi> having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Gun-Powder in the Year of our Lord 1380. under the Reign of <hi>Wenceſlaus.</hi> the Son of <hi>Charles</hi> IV, the Cannon and other pieces of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery were then applied to beat down theſe weak defences, which was done without much difficulty, whereupon the beſieged were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to reinforce their Walls, to enlarge their Towers, and to give them another Figure, which gave occaſion to the invention of Baſtions and other Works that are now in uſe.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Book is laid down the<note n="(n)" place="margin">21.</note> Maxims and Rules of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, reſerving the illuſtration of ſome of them for the fourth Book. Afterwards he enquires into the advantages and diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Situation of Places, built on a Rock, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as alſo that of Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels and other ſmall Fortreſſes which ſerve to command the plain Country: But as for great places he determines that they cannot be better ſituated than in a Plain, or rather on the Banks of a large River: Then he proceeds to diſcourſe of the nature and<note n="(p)" place="margin">30.</note> quality of the earth, and prefers that ſort which is fat and pliable as the beſt for theſe Works. Laſtly, he concludes this Book, with giving ſome account of neceſſary<note n="(q)" place="margin">32.</note> Proviſions and Ammunition; and it is not without good reaſon that he makes mention of Money in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Catalogue.</p>
               <p>Moreover in the third Book the Author ſhews, after<note n="(r)" place="margin">33.</note> what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner a regular Polygon may be inſcribed within a given Circle, and how to make a Scale; he proceeds to repreſent the<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">35.</note> draught of a Square, as being the firſt figure propounded to be Fortified; then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving explained the<note n="(t)" place="margin">40.</note> conſtruction of the exteriour parts, he returns, to that of the<note n="(u)" place="margin">50.</note> Polygons: Laſtly, he exhibits the manner of making,<note n="(x)" place="margin">53.</note> 
                  <hi>Profils</hi> or Draughts, of drawing out<note n="(y)" place="margin">55.</note> a Fortreſs in the Field, and of deſcribing<note n="(z)" place="margin">57.</note> the Streets in a Draught.</p>
               <p>To prove in ſome meaſure what he hath alledged, and give a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er light into the knowledge of this Art, he produces in the fourth Book<note n="(aa)" place="margin">59.88.</note> the different ſentiments of a great number of Engineers, concerning the moſt principal parts of Fortification, and afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his own opinion. We ſhall now give a particular account of the moſt conſiderable remarks that have been made on the Method of this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54947:20"/>famous Engineer. Let us then begin with the Flanks which are the principal parts of Fortification, therefore nothing ought to be neglected for the moſt advantageous ſtructure of them. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the largeſt are undoubtedly the beſt, Monſieur <hi>de Vauban</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to allow them as much height as is poſſible. It is for this reaſon that he will not admit a ſecond Flank, and that he makes the Overture of the Angle of the Curtain to conſiſt of from 98 to 106 degrees. Thus the Flanks in his middle-ſiz'd Fortification, which we ſhall only mention here, contain from 18 to 37 Fathoms. I cannot imagine that it will be objected, that he doth not regulate the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Angle of the Curtain with a due proportion to the ſaid Curtain; ſince its heighth ought only to be determined with reſpect to the Line of Defence. This ſeems to be that which this great Man chiefly regarded. Monſieur <hi>de Vauban</hi> having allowed to the Flanks all the length imaginable, endeavours to cover part of them as much as is poſſible; to this purpoſe he erects an <hi>Orillon,</hi> which he forms out of a Semi-Circle. Perhaps it will be thought to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what unuſual that he conſtantly makes it to conſiſt of the third part of the Flank, becauſe it doth not ſeem to be neceſſary to erect a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>Orillon</hi> in a greater Fortification than in a leſſer. I am apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that it is ſufficient to allow it ſo much ſtrength as to be able to reſiſt the force of the Cannon. Afterwards he cauſeth the two other parts of the Flank to return within the body of the Baſtion, aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the Figure of the ſixth part of a Circle, and this is what hath been lately termed the <hi>hollow Tower,</hi> or <hi>Flank retired.</hi> Laſtly, for the better covering of the Flanks, he placeth the wings of the Works which he builds before the Curtain within the Faces, at the diſtance of ſome Fathoms from the <hi>Orillon.</hi> It hath been believed for a long time, that double Flanks were of very great uſe in the defence of a place, but they are wholly omitted by Monſieur <hi>de Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> tho' his reaſons are not as yet well known: neither doth he regard <hi>Falſe-Brayes,</hi> which is not to be admir'd; and to defend the Trench, he makes uſe of a ſmall and low <hi>Tenail</hi> to very good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, which he placeth before the Curtain, and is ſeparated from it by a little ditch. The Faces of this Work are in the ſame deline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation with thoſe of the Baſtions. The Flanks are diſtant from the others from 10 to 12 Fathoms, and Monſieur <hi>de Cambray</hi> declares that this proves what he had before aſſerted concerning the Line of Defence, for he had avouched in one of his Maxims, that it ought not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54947:21"/>to exceed 125 Fathoms, nevertheleſs it appears from his Tables that it contains from 126 to 138 Fathoms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There needs not much pains to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with reſpect to the Angle of the Baſtion, only aſſigning to it from 60 to 100 degrees, that it may be able to ſuſtain it ſelf, and that the Baſtion may be of a ſufficient largeneſs. But as for the Faces they ſeem to require more care to make them of an equal ſtrength, ſince they do not exceed at moſt above 50 fathoms. Laſtly, touching the Trench, the Author follows the opinion of Monſieur <hi>de Clermont,</hi> who allots from 18 to twenty fathoms for its breadth, and from 18 to 20 feet for its depth. The <hi>Glacis</hi>'s are made as large as they can be conveniently, not allowing leſs to them than 36 fathoms; but as for the Rampart, its breadth is limited to 10 fathoms, and Monſieur <hi>de Vauban</hi> derides their project that would have it proportioned to the largeneſs of the Polygons, as if little places were not attacked with the ſame Arms as thoſe that are greater.</p>
               <p>In the fifth and laſt Book, the Author ſhews<note n="(bb)" place="margin">89.</note> the ſtructure of divers Fortreſſes erected in the Field, and afterwards lays down<note n="(cc)" place="margin">95.</note> Rules for the fortifying of an irregular place. But as to the method uſed by him, it may be affirmed, that he departs a little from his own Maxims, and more eſpecially from the firſt; in regard that the Trench, the Baſe of the Rampart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are diminiſhed proportionably as the ſide of the Polygon exceeds 180 fathoms, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs one would ſay, that in Triangles, which are unequal, there is the ſame proportion between their ſides. This Book is concluded with mentioning ſomewhat concerning Artillery, whilſt a larger diſcourſe thereof is reſerved to a Treatiſe wherein the Author promiſes expreſly to inform us of the manner of attacking a place according to the judgment of Monſieur <hi>de Vauban,</hi> the publication of which is impatiently expected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:54947:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> OSTEOLOGIA NOVA: Or, A New Treatiſe of the Bones, and the Parts belonging to them; with the Manner of their Growth and Nutrition: Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Royal Society</hi> in ſeveral Diſcourſes; By <hi>Clopton Havers</hi> M. D. Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi> London, <hi>for</hi> S. Smith, <hi>1691. Pag. 310.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT would require a Diſcourſe as large as any of the Five Diſſerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Dr. <hi>Haver</hi>'s Book, ſhould we go about to ſet down every Thing that is new and curious therein: And therefore the extraordinary Abundance of Matter will enforce us to paſs over many remarkable Things upon which we ſhould have inſiſted much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; but that they are, as we may ſay, ſo heap'd up in Piles one upon another.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The Firſt Diſcourſe treats of the Nature of Bones, and deſcribes the Membrane which covers them, their interiour Frame and Figure.</p>
               <p>The Author begins with a kind of Prologue, very ſignificant to the purpoſe; by giving an <hi>Idea</hi> of the manner of Generation, according to the Principles of <hi>de Graef,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Drelincourt.</hi> He ſuppoſes,<note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 7.</note> That all the Parts of the Creature are delineated in the Female's Egg, while it is yet in the Womb, and before the Seed of the Male has given it Life: That the moſt volatile Parts of the Seed inſinuating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Umbilical Vein of the Egg, through the Pores of the Membrane of the <hi>Ovary,</hi> that Vein carries thoſe Particles to the two Ventricles of the Heart, where they raiſe a Fermentation in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors which there they meet withal, that rarifies and dilates them, and putting the Fibres of the Heart upon a Contraction, produces that Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which is the Sign and Beginning of Life. Part of theſe rarify'd Humors falling from the right and left Ventricles, into the <hi>Aorta,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts its Motion to the Matter contained in it, and in all the Veſſels which depend upon it. The Arteries being thus extended, and the Liquor within them being agitated, opens its ſelf a Paſſage through the Veins; and this compleats the Circulation. Theſe Humors thus
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54947:22"/>circulating, meet with Glandules in their way, upon the ſides, and at the Extremities of the Arteries, through which there is a neceſſity for them to paſs. Theſe Glandules being a ſort of Strainers, the moſt ſubtle Parts and thoſe which firſt get through the Glandules of the Brain, are thoſe which are call'd the <hi>Vital and Animal Spirits;</hi> of which, when there are ſufficient to give motion to the Original of the Nerves, then apparently it is, that the Soul is infus'd into the <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Membrane<note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 14.</note> which covers the Bone, is very thin, and exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely ſenſible, and made up of moſt minute and curious Threds, which deduce their Original from the <hi>Dura Mater,</hi> and from ſeveral Muſcles and Tendons. Thoſe that deſcend from the <hi>Dura Mater,</hi> lie the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the Bones, and are all parallel; but thoſe which proceed from the Muſcles, take a different courſe, according to the ſituation of the Muſcle from whence they proceed. This Membrane is faſtned to the Bone by the nature of their Subſtance, which is viſcous and ſlimy, and by certain little Fibres of that Membrane, which enter into the Pores of the Bone. It is appointed for Five ſeveral Offices:
<list>
                     <item>1. It ſerves to cover the Bones.</item>
                     <item>2. It conveys Spirits into their Subſtance, which preſerve their Heat, render them ſenſible, and aſſiſt them in their growth and nouriſhment.</item>
                     <item>3. It contributes to limit the growth of the Bones.</item>
                     <item>4. It ſerves to keep them joyn'd and knit together, and with the Tendons of the Muſcles</item>
                     <item>5. This Membrane being extreamly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, cauſes us to feel the leaſt Diſorder that happens in the ſtructure of the Bones, and directs us in the Application of outward Remedies to the Place affected.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Bones,<note n="(c)" place="margin">p. 30.</note> at their firſt beginning, are no more than a clammy Gelly; which drying by little and little, becomes a Griſtle<note n="*" place="margin">Carti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage.</note>, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards a perfect Bone, by the evaporation of the liquid Matter, and the additions of the nutritive Juice. The Particles that compoſe them, are long in ſhape, and of a terreſtrial and ſalt Nature; but the terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Particles make above two Thirds of the Maſs. Their Fibres are long; contig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous, and parallel one to the other, in ſuch a manner that they form little Lamels; which meeting at the Extremity of the Bones, lie one over another, and cloſe up the Concavity<note n="(d)" place="margin">p. 43.</note>. There are two ſorts of Pores in the Bones, beſides thoſe which ſerve for a paſſage to the Sanguinary Veſſels: of which ſome are oblique, and pierce through the Lamels of the Bones, extending themſelves from the ſuperficies of the Bone to the Hollowneſs; the other are ſtreight and narrow, and appear all along the Lamels from one end of the Bone to the other.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54947:22"/>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">p 49.</note> The Superficies of the Bone is very uneven, unleſs it be at the Joints, where there is a neceſſity it ſhould be ſmoother; to facilitate the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Parts. This unevenneſs proceeds from the ſuperficial Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities and Pores, which there meet together. Theſe ſuperficial Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities are of two ſorts: Some are long, and like a ſort of Furrows; others are ſhorter, and of a different ſhape. The Uſe of both is to dilate the Surface of the Bone, and to keep the Membrane more firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faſtned to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note> As for the Pores, their Uſe is to ſerve as paſſages for Blood. Veſſels; ſome belonging to thoſe Veſſels which convey that Blood which ſupplies the nutritious Juice; others, to them which ſerve to the Marrow. Thoſe of the nutritious Veins are very numerous, but ſo ſmall, that it is a difficult thing to diſcern them. Thoſe of the Medullary Arteries are more remarkable, and enter the Bone obliquely; ſo that the way which they make, is often Ten or Twelve times lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the Thickneſs of the Bone.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">p. 61.</note> There are two ſorts of Hollowneſſes in the Bone; and of thoſe which are large, there is but one in every Bone; the reſt are very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, and reſemble little Cells, which render that part of the Bone ſpungy where they are to be found. The Author gives the Reaſons of all this Structure of Nature.</p>
               <p>You will alſo find there very curious Obſervations upon the Teeth.<note n="(h)" place="margin">p. 78.</note> Dr. <hi>Havers</hi> obſerves, That they are made up of two very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Parts: The one is of the Nature of Stones, having the ſolidity and glittering of the hardeſt Flints; but with this difference, that they will be diſſolv'd by <hi>Aqua Fortis,</hi> which Flints will not. This Stony Matter is a ſort of Rind, which covers all the Part without the Gums. That Part which is within the Gums is cover'd with a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Membrane, which nevertheleſs proceeds not from that of the Jaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, though this Membrane extends it ſelf to the Faſtning or Incloſure of the Teeth in the Gums, and be contiguous to their Membrane.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The Second Diſcourſe<note n="(i)" place="margin">p 89.</note> treats at firſt of <hi>Growth</hi> and <hi>Nouriſhment</hi> in general; which the Author afterwards particularly applies to the Bones. He reduces all that Matter to Three Queſtions. The Firſt, How the Nutritive Juice is form'd, and fix'd to the Parts of young Creatures, after ſuch a ſort as to enlarge their Dimenſions? Certain it is, that that ſame Juice proceeds from our Nouriſhment chang'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chyle; which paſſing through the Milky Veins, to mix it ſelf with the Blood, meets with ſome Particles of the Nutritive Juice of the Kerneſs, convey'd by the Lymphatick Chanels, that ſerve for a Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54947:23"/>to thoſe of the Chyle. This Milky Liquor entring the Heart, and being mix'd with the Blood, is there ſubtiliz'd, and paſſes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards into the Arteries; on the ſides of which it meets with Kernels, the Pores of which are ſo fram'd, as only to admit the Nutritive Juice.</p>
               <p>Now while the reſt of the Blood purſues its Courſe in the Artery, the Nutritive Particles are preſs'd out of the Kernels, and advance forward through every up-lifting of the Artery, and by the preſſure of other little Bodies of the ſame nature, which ſupply their Places, till they are puſh'd forward into the Intervals of the Fibres, where they meet with the Spirits in Motion.</p>
               <p>Theſe Spirits have a double Motion; for they turn about their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre like a Bowl thrown out of hand, while according to their local Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they deſcribe a Line as ſtreight as is poſſible. Now in regard the Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritive Parts are liquid and viſcous, and that the Spirits cannot impart their direct Motion to them, they force them to the ſides of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, where they ſtick; more eſpecially, if they meet with any hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or any void ſpace. Add to this, that while the Creature is yet very young, the Parts are very tender, and the Fibres more ſupple, and leſs extended: So that it is no wonder if little viſcous Bodies being forced in between the Extremities of the Particles of thoſe Fibres, theſe ſoft Parts give way, and ſo ſeparate one from the other, for the infixation of new Matter.</p>
               <p>The Second Queſtion,<note n="(k)" place="margin">p. 126.</note> propoſes, What is the Cauſe that ſtops the growth of any Creature? To which, the Anſwer is, That it is the hardneſs of the Filaments and Lamels, and the firm unition of the Particles of the Fleſhy and Nervous Fibres, which, when a Creature is come to ſuch an Age, reſiſt the Efforts of the Spirits and Nutritive Particles; ſo that not being able to lodge themſelves in the Pores or Intervals of the Fibres, which are already full, they are carried off by the direct motion of the Spirits, to other Kernels, which rarifie them to a greater degree, and employ them to other Uſes.</p>
               <p>The Third Queſtion<note n="(l)" place="margin">p. 133.</note> is about Nouriſhment, the Nature of it, and how it is perform'd? Dr. <hi>Havers</hi> believes it to be no more than a continual Supply of the fluid and nutritious Particles that keep the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, the Pores, the Hollowneſſes, and in a word, all the Pipes and Veſſels of the Body full, and in a good condition. Sometimes it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens that there may be a loſs of ſome part of the Fibres, and that the void ſpace is fill'd up by the Nutritive Juice, which the circular Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirits forces forward, toward the ſides of the Arteries:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54947:23"/>But this, the Author ſays, is not the manner of Nature's repairing the ordinary Decays and Waſts of our Bodies.</p>
               <p>For Proof of which, he ſuppoſes, as another Learned Anatomiſt<note n="*" place="margin">D. <hi>Tyſon.</hi>
                  </note> does, that the whole Body of Man is porous, and full of Veſſels, which ſeveral ſorts of Humors keep dilated and well ſill'd; ſo that Leanneſs, and the <hi>Maraſm</hi> it ſelf, do not proceed from that, the fix'd Parts of our Body, as the Fleſh and Bones are depriv'd of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; which can never happen but by the violence of Corroſives, which would cauſe an incredible pain: nevertheleſs they feel no pain who are troubled with thoſe languiſhing Diſeaſes: And therefore ſuch an <hi>Atrophy</hi> muſt proceed from hence, that the Humors which fill the Veſſels, and preſerve them plump, evaporating the Veſſels ſhrunk, and by that means impair the Dimenſion of the Parts.</p>
               <p>The Author afterwards,<note n="(m)" place="margin">p 143.</note> makes the Application of his Principles, to explain the manner, and the limits of the growth of the Bones, and how they are nouriſhed; which it is no difficult thing to do, if the Reader forget not what has been already obſerv'd; That both in the <hi>Foetus</hi> and a new born Child, the Bones are made up of a Matter which is very tender, and eaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y gives way; but as it grows, changes into G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles that the Particles which compoſe the Griſtles, do not form con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Threads, but leave between them Cavities, or void Spaces, which in time are fill'd up with Nutritive Juice! That it ſlides along a good while before all the Spaces of thoſe Particles are fill'd up, and that the Griſtles are converted into perfect Bones; and then it is that Growth ceaſes, the Nutritious Particles no longer knowing where to lodge themſelves. According to this <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Havers</hi> explains the Reaſon why the Bones grow crooked in the <hi>Rickets,</hi> and why both that Diſtemper and the <hi>Neapolitan Diſeaſe</hi> many times produce Knots or Excreſcencies upon the Bone.</p>
               <p n="3">III. The Third Diſcourſe treats of the <hi>Marrow.</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">p. 161</note> All the World knows that the <hi>Marrow</hi> is an Oyly Subſtance, which fills the Cavity of the Bones; but you ſhall hardly any where elſe meet with ſo exact a Deſcription of it, as the Author gives here: This Marrow is enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſmall round Veſicles; of which two, or three, or more, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in Bags of different ſhape, and theſe Bags in a tranſparent and very ſlender Membrane, conſiſting of Fibres prolong'd from the Blood-Veſſels, which afford it Nouriſhment through the Pores of the Bones. Theſe Veſicles and little Bags are alſo furniſhed with Pores, through which the Marrow's Oyl paſſes from one to the other, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates it ſelf to the Joints: So that theſe Veſicles are alſo a kind of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54947:24"/>Kernels, and ſeparate the Marrow from the other Parts of the Blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">p. 171.</note> When theſe Veſicles are full, they contract themſelves, as all puffed up Bladders do, and then diſcharging their Oil the one into the other, it paſſes from Veſicle to Veſicle, and from Bag to Bag, till it enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the thwarting Pores of the Bones; whence it ſheds it ſelf into the ſtreight Pores, and at the Articulations, and is employed into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities between their Joints, which it keeps moiſt and ſlippery. In the great Cavities of the Bones, the Marrow appears whitiſh, ſpeckled with Red; but abſolutely Red in the leſſer Cells, which only proceeds from the different quantity of Veins and Arteries that nouriſh it: Some parts of this Marrow are apt to congeal, becauſe they are mix'd with Nitre.</p>
               <p>Though the Marrow<note n="(p)" place="margin">p. 178.</note> contributes nothing to the Nouriſhment of the Bones, that are furniſhed with Blood-Veſſels appointed for that purpoſe; it is otherwiſe many ways uſeful: For,
<list>
                     <item>1. It moiſtens the Subſtance of the Bones, and by its oyly Nature it preſerves them in good condition, and hinders them from ſhivering.</item>
                     <item>2. With the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilage it makes the Joints of the Bones ſlippery, and conſequently ſit for Motion.</item>
                     <item>3. Mixt with the clammy Mucilage, it cools them, and prevents their contracting a more than ordinary Heat by their Motion.</item>
                     <item>4. It prevents them from wearing out, waſting and bruiſing by rubbing one againſt another.</item>
                     <item>5. It is after the ſame manner ſerviceable to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments which tie the Bones together, preſerving them from being dry and ſtiff, and keeping them ſupple and ſlippery.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. The Fourth Diſcourſe treats of the Mucilage, and the mucilaginous Kernels<note n="(q)" place="margin">p. 187.</note> Theſe Kernels are one of the principal Diſcoveries of the Author; who tells us, they were never diſcerned by any perſon before himſelf. They are of two ſorts; the one ſort, which is very ſmall and numerous, take up the whole Membrane of the Joint, unleſs in that part where you meet with the ſecond ſort of theſe Kernels, which are conglomerate, bigger, and conſequently more remarkable than the firſt. They are made up of ſeveral Kernels, or ſmall Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes, extended one upon another, long and large at the bottom, and ending uſually in a point, though there are ſome that are flat, and of other different Figures. They are ſoft and ſupple, and not brittle; ſo that they yield to, and ſuffer the impreſſion of the Bones without receiving any harm. The Blood-Veſſels with which they communicate, are not ſtreight, but oblique; ſo that the Blood circulating round about them, the mucilaginous Particles have time to ſeparate, when they enter the Kernels.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:54947:24"/>The Mucilage<note n="(r)" place="margin">p 201.</note> which diſtills out of theſe Kernels, is a clear and clammy Liquor, almoſt like the White of an Egg. It is compoſed of Watry, Salt and Terreſtrial Parts; but the Salt, and the Earthy Parts make no more than about the 32d part of the Mixture. It partakes of the nature of the <hi>Serum,</hi> only that it is not to be all turn'd into a <hi>Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulum</hi> by the heat of the Fire, as the <hi>Serum</hi> is. It ſerves for the ſame Uſe as the Marrow, and they aſſiſt one another to perform their Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The Mucilage renders the Marrow's Oyl more ſlippery, and that Oyl hinders the Mucilage from growing too thick. It is formed, as the Author ſays, in the Spleen, which is of a Viſcous and Kernelly Subſtance, and which has two forts of Pores; the one proper for the diſtilling of <hi>Acids</hi> through them, and the other is a Stiptick Juice, which ſerves as a Ferment for the Blood to produce the Mucilage there. Dr. <hi>Havers</hi> ſets down ſeveral Experiments<note n="(s)" place="margin">p. 217.</note> which he has made upon this Liquor; of which, the moſt conſiderable, in relation to Phyſick, are, That violent <hi>Acids,</hi> as <hi>Salt,</hi> and Oyl of <hi>Vitriol, Aqua fortis,</hi> and Spirit of <hi>Nitre,</hi> and <hi>Vinegar,</hi> coagulate the Mucilage, chiefly when it is hot; ſo that it will become thin and fluid, and that you may ſeparate from it a kind of <hi>Whey,</hi> or <hi>Serum.</hi> The Author tried, whether by the help of Powder of <hi>Coral, Antimony Diaphorerick,</hi> or <hi>Crabs-Eyes,</hi> he could make it reſume its firſt Nature; but he could not bring it to paſs: Yet with <hi>Spirit of Sal Armon.</hi> and <hi>Salt of Tartar,</hi> all the Coagulation would be diſſolved.</p>
               <p>The Parts where theſe Kernels are ſeated, are ſubject to <hi>Catarrh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> becauſe theſe Kernels not only ſeparate the Mucilage from the Blood, but many times alſo other Morbiſick Humors, which Nature deſires to be rid of. When thoſe Humors affect the Muſcies, they cauſe the <hi>Rheumatiſm,</hi> and when they fall upon the Joints, they breed the <hi>Gout.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Havers</hi> beſtows a whole Article<note n="(t)" place="margin">p. 223, 249.</note> upon both theſe Diſtempers, and obſerves, that the Humors which infect the Mucilage upon theſe occaſions, are of three ſorts; the one ſharp and thin, the other ſalt, und the laſt, which are the moſt uſual, acid and corroding. You will read with delight the Author's manner of explaining the three Sources of theſe Diſtempers; which gives a great Light to underſtand their Cure.</p>
               <p n="5">V. The Fifth Diſcourſe is concerning the <hi>Griſtles,</hi>
                  <note n="(u)" place="margin">p. 288.</note> It has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready obſerv'd, that they are only imperfect Bones; which being ſubtle and flexible, are apt to comply with the ſeveral motions of the Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. The Author deſcribes at large their Nature, and their outward
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54947:25"/>and inward Structure, as alſo their different Uſes; and particularly of thoſe in the Breaſt, p. 284.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II. <hi>FREDERICI R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ISCHII, Anatomes, Chyrurgiae &amp; Botanices Profeſſoris, Obſervationum Anatomico-Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum Centuria.</hi> Accedit Catalogus Rariorum quae in Muſaeo <hi>Ruyſchiano</hi> aſſervantur, adjectis ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> I conibus aeneis naturalem magnitudinem repreſentantibus. <hi>Amſtelod.</hi> apud <hi>H. Boom</hi> 1691. pag. 274. Proſtant apud <hi>Abel Swall,</hi> &amp; <hi>Timo. Childe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are few Books that look more curious to the ſight than this. The Paper, the Print, the Figures, draw the Eyes of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and there is no body but will give a favourable Judgment of the Work, when he reads in the Preface, that the Author has been Twenty Years Profeſſor of <hi>Anatomy</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam:</hi> That he has had all the Conveniencies in the World to make Experiments in the Hoſpitals of that great City; and that he has ſpent all his Life in making Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of whatever he has obſerved moſt remarkable. Upon theſe Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations it is, that he has rais'd the Hundred Obſervations which compoſe the firſt Part of this Work. The Second, is a Deſcription of the Author's Study; where are to be ſeen ſeveral Rarities of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Ruyſchius</hi> is not of the number of thoſe that build in the Air a Syſteme of Phyſick, which has no other Foundation than Chimerical Conjectures. He maintains, that Experience only is the Miſtreſs of that Art; and he adviſes, that Men, inſtead of gueſſing at the Cauſes of Diſeaſes, ſhould chiefly buſie themſelves in collecting together the moſt ſurprizing <hi>Phanomena's</hi> that offer themſelves in Practice. But withal, it would be neceſſary, that all who undertake this Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould have ſeen every thing with their own Eyes, and that they ſhould be endued with a Conception and Judgment ſo ſufficiently clear, as not to look upon as extraordinary Accidents, Things that happen every day.</p>
               <p>The cutting of an Artery<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ob.</hi> 11. p. 5.</note>, eſpecially in the larger Veſſels, is an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident difficult to cure; and the Author would have obliged the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, had he explained a little more at large how he ſtopt that <hi>Aneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſma</hi> in the Arm, to the Cure of which he ſays he was an Aſſiſtant. When he prepared to make the Inciſion, to diſcover the wounded Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54947:25"/>that he might cloſe it up again, he ſays, he made uſe of an Iron-Ring, lin'd with a thick and ſoft Skin, which he intended to apply to the upper part of the Arm, above the <hi>Aneuriſma,</hi> to ſtop the motion of the Blood that way; That that ſame Inſtrument not anſwering their expectation, they had recourſe to another, which took effect; but the Author is ſo far from deſcribing it, that he does not ſo much as name it. In a Journal of Eight Days, relating to that Malady, which Mr. <hi>Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchius</hi> gives us, we find the Wound grew continually worſe and worſe, till it broke out into two new <hi>Aneuriſma's;</hi> the one of which being as large as a great Pea, open'd it ſelf, but bled not much; becauſe the Chirurgeon ſtopt it preſently; and a few days after, it was through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly healed, by opening the Vein, a ſlender Diet, and a due compreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. As for the other, they had much ado to ſqueeze it down; it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſeveral days, but at length it vaniſh'd, and the Patient reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. <hi>Paucis diebus ſecta Vena, tenuiori diaeta praeſcripta, &amp; debita com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſione facta, ſanatum fuit. Alterum vero Aneuriſma quantumvis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primeretur perplures dies, curationi remoram fecit; tandem vero quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit, convaluit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aeger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would be a ſtrange Thing<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> 22. p. 27.</note> that a Woman ſhould conceive, and yet that the Membrane call'd the <hi>Hymen,</hi> ſhould not be broken. But the Relation which Mr. <hi>Ruyſchius</hi> gives us, is not ſufficient to make us believe it. He adds another Circumſtance more incredible; aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, That the <hi>Vagina</hi> or Sheath of the Womb was covered and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up with an extraordinary Membrane at the Time of the Woman's Lying in. He ſays, That theſe two Membranes were cut, and that the Infant came forth ſound and vigorous, and that the Mother recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved no harm. However, in my Opinion, there is nothing in this Relation of his, but what might have been unfolded, without ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any thing but what is very common. The Bed wherein the <hi>Foetus</hi> is contained, and which is made up of ſeveral double Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes, ſinks down by little and little, through the weight of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that fill it. Then the Infant ſeparates from the Body of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and falls with his Head downward toward the Orifice of the Womb. Many times it happens that the <hi>Foetus</hi> falls on the Side, and incumbers it ſelf, Head and Neck together, in the Membranes of its Bed. Thoſe, it ſeems, were the Membranes which <hi>Ruyſchius</hi> cauſed to be cut, and which hindred the Birth of the Infant: At leaſt there is nothing in all his Obſervation, which forces us to have recourſe to two ſuch wonderful Events.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:54947:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> Leonardi Plukenetri <hi>PHYTOGRAPHIA,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium Illuſtriorum, &amp; minùs cognitarum <hi>I CONES,</hi> Tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis aeneis, <hi>120</hi> Fig. fere, <hi>800.</hi> ſummâ diligentra elaboratoe. Fol. <hi>Londini 1691.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHerein the Author has given impregnant Inſtance at his own expence, of his earneſt deſire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of improving <hi>Bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y.</hi> The Subject of this Book h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s been the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>died Collection of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vears, and unites in it ſelf the ſcattered and moſt diſtant Parts of <hi>Vegetable Nature;</hi> which if we conſider as to their <hi>Number</hi> or <hi>Novelty,</hi> it will appear ſuch an Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omulation of <hi>Network Science,</hi> as few Books of this Nature can boaſt of: Not can we ſufficiently admire the vaſt Variety of curiouſly engra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ent or unheard of Plants commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to the World in ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ior<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and compendious a Volu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod he takes in explaining theſe E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ticks, is both conſpicuous and fuccirct; his Names adapted from their eſſential Notes, and proper Characteriſticks, ſuch, as without help of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> might convey to the Mind a true <hi>Idea</hi> of the Things they denominate, as being entire De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of them.</p>
               <p>The Work divides it ſelf into Two Parts; and by a freſh addition of Parts, may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ngt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>linect out <hi>ad infi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> For our Author pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues the Alphabetical Order in his Deſign; yet not ſo as to break in upon <hi>Affinities</hi> or <hi>Cognations,</hi> but had rather commute a Name, than not preſerve a <hi>Clan</hi> or <hi>Tribe,</hi> as may be obſerved throughout the whole Work: As, for inſtance, what others call a <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>es Africana Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> Pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtris fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> with be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reaſon he terms a <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o,</hi> and ranks i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> among its Cognominals in the Letter <hi>B.</hi> By this way of exploding improper Appellations, and aſſigning new ones to ſome late diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Plants, he comes to aſſert the ſtragling Vegetable into its proper Family; and ſuch Alliances that lay before promiſcuous, or disjoyned, and ſtood at diſtance with each other, into a cloſer kind of <hi>Conſorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> Thus, the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e Orienta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> fruo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of others, (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is no <hi>Alcea,</hi>) is made by him, a <hi>Lapp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> tetraſperm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and ſubjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>atina Trag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Hiſt. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gd,</hi> which is a <hi>Tetraſpermo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> too; (by many, moſt untruly ſtiled a <hi>Cynogloſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>) as of more congruity with it, and near akin thereto; and in this way of Diſtribution, he ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves both <hi>Alphab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How clear his Art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igurations has made that cloudy <hi>Stella Legu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minoſa</hi> of the Great <hi>John Bauhine,</hi> when here, as through a Beam of Light, it manifeſts it ſelf a true <hi>Aſtragalus,</hi> and diſcrepant from all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54947:26"/>others of the Kind. The <hi>Jacca's,</hi> however perplex'd in other Authors, are ſet to rights in this; and <hi>Thapſla's,</hi> no leſs confus'd, are here di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct in the <hi>Iconiſms</hi> of our Author.</p>
               <p>There are ſome of thoſe many curious Figures, the needful Emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of vitiate or miſtaken <hi>Icons</hi> in elder Authors, which are by him made genuine from the Truth of Things, on purpoſe to clear the Doubts, and decide the Controverſies of our moſt celebrious <hi>Moderus:</hi> This he eſteems a Service done the Publick, as well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves his Pains, and equal to that of introducing Plants <hi>de novo.</hi> A rare Example of this kind, is the <hi>Jacea fruticans Pini folio</hi> of the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Caſpar Bauhine,</hi> which from the miſerable Cut in <hi>Pona,</hi> in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Mount <hi>Baldus,</hi> under the Title of <hi>Staebe capitata Roſmarini folio;</hi> from whence all later Writers derive their Pictures of it, hath been ſo puzling to the moſt ſagacious <hi>Botaniſts</hi> of this preſent Age, that it hath been wellnigh loſt in their ſuſpicion of its being the ſame with the <hi>Stachas purpurea</hi> of <hi>Peliterius,</hi> in the Illuſtrations of <hi>Lobel.</hi> That Figure of it in <hi>Proſper Alpinus</hi> his <hi>Exoticks,</hi> pag. 77. under the Name of <hi>Chamaepeuce,</hi> is indeed more tolerable; but much inferiour to this Noble and Illuſtrious <hi>Knapweed,</hi> which owes its Reſtauration to the more ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urate and lively graven Image of our Author.</p>
               <p>Whoſe ſtudious care in ſtating References to obſcurer, and leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible Writers, as <hi>Marcgrave, Laet,</hi> and <hi>Hernandez,</hi> he takes to be a proper means to eaſe Nature of the Tympany ſome others would affect her with, by multiplying <hi>Species</hi> without ſenſe or reaſon; in their propoſing Plants for new, which under other Names are to be found in the dark Obſcurities of former Writers.</p>
               <p>But let us now deſcend to ſome Particulars of the many hundred rare <hi>Exotick</hi> Plants this Author repreſents to view in curious Sculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for to recount them all, were to tranſcribe the Book it ſelf.</p>
               <p>He there preſents you with a ſtranger <hi>Maple</hi> from <hi>Bengal,</hi> that hath the Leaves of Bay; with an Herbaceous Plant from <hi>China,</hi> from which they raſe their <hi>Moxa,</hi> ſo celebrated all over <hi>India</hi> for curing of the Gout. He gives you Three ſorts of <hi>Serpentaria,</hi> the Roots whereof are Remedy againſt the Bitings of the <hi>Rattle-Snake;</hi> two from <hi>Virginia,</hi> and one from <hi>Maryland,</hi> all boaſted Antidotes of <hi>America:</hi> There is another from thoſe Parts, they call a <hi>Serpintary,</hi> figur'd in his firſt Appendix with a fattiſll <hi>Birthwort</hi> or <hi>Briony</hi> ſort of Leaf, and a long Scries of ſtamineous Flowers diſpos'd into a Spike; with a jointed creeping Root, much differing from the former, a Plant of its own kind, and truly Heteroclital. Moreover, he gives a true and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54947:27"/>genuine Figure of the <hi>Ninzeng,</hi> or <hi>Ginzeng,</hi> together with its Root, of great value in its Native Country, it being eſteem'd a <hi>Panacea</hi> throughout the <hi>Oriental Indies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He obliges the World with ſeveral rare <hi>Adianthums</hi> from <hi>China</hi> and elſewhere, with various <hi>Amaranths,</hi> and <hi>Amaranthioides</hi> from both the <hi>Indies;</hi> an odd ſort of <hi>Antirrhinum</hi> with very ſlender Leaves turn'd up like Muſtachoes; and that <hi>Peruvian,</hi> Shrub ſo oſtentatiouſly ſhewn by ſome, for the Tree, from whence the <hi>Jeſuit's Bark</hi> is taken, ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Remedy for all ſorts of <hi>Fevers:</hi> He propoſes to the World a numerous Train of <hi>Indian Graſſes</hi> unknown before to <hi>Europe;</hi> among the reſt, a moſt illuſtrious ſort, one of the Glories of <hi>Carolina:</hi> Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral new and elegant <hi>Evonymi</hi> from <hi>America,</hi> and one from <hi>Maderoſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> with Leaves not much unlike that ſort of <hi>Caſſia lignea,</hi> that's co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with the Bark of <hi>Winterane.</hi> The <hi>Indian Tea,</hi> with its Fruit and Flower, by him ſtil'd <hi>Evonymo adſinis nucifera Orientalis;</hi> as alſo that other <hi>Evonymo adfinis Occidentalis alatis Ruſci foliis nucifera,</hi> which at its firſt arrival, came under the Name of <hi>Jaſminum Americanum,</hi> and is the <hi>Guaiacum folio Lentiſci</hi> of the <hi>Fagel</hi> Garden, in the ſecond <hi>Prodromus</hi> of <hi>Jacobus Breynius.</hi> He alſo pronoſes to your view in this moſt excellent Work, two ſorts of the true <hi>Guaiacum,</hi> or <hi>Indian Pockwood,</hi> with their Flower and Fruit. Several kinds of <hi>Hemionitis</hi> from <hi>Antego, Wales,</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt Indies;</hi> and one eſpecially of the Compoſite Order, akin to this Moon-Fern Family, with petalous and perfect Flowers growing to the Crenatures, upon the Rim, and on the back-part of the Leaves, a goodly Native of the flouriſhing Iſland of <hi>Jamaica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Liquid Amber,</hi> or <hi>Storax</hi> Tree of the <hi>West Indies,</hi> together with its Fruit; which ſhews it to be neither <hi>Platanus</hi> nor <hi>Acer,</hi> are here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited in <hi>Icon.</hi> The <hi>Cock ſpurs,</hi> together with the Plum-leav'd Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of <hi>Virginia,</hi> without Thorns, are here diſtinctly plac'd. That kind of <hi>Baſtard-Myrile</hi> from <hi>Bermudos,</hi> ſo like the <hi>Elaeagnus Cordi,</hi> which our Author, with good reaſon, takes to be the ſame with <hi>Laurus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata odora</hi> of the Cape, in the Learned Commentaries of <hi>Bodaeus a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;</hi> another moſt elegant bacciſerous kind from <hi>Carolina,</hi> that bears its Berries on its Branches in cluſters, like ſo many rugged Coriander-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits; and a Third Sort, both Juliferous, and Fruit-bearing, with an echi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Fruit, like the prickly <hi>Involucrum</hi> of a ſmall Cheſnut, and Leaves of the Tree like our <hi>Aſplenium.</hi> An <hi>Onobrychis,</hi> with the Face of a <hi>Mimoſa,</hi> from the Kingdom of <hi>Biſnagar.</hi> Another with a ſingle Leaf, from one of the Mouths of the River <hi>Ganges;</hi> and a Third, bifoliate, from <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſpatan,</hi> are the ſurprizing Wonders of Botanick Nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:54947:27"/>A mimerous Tribe of ſtrange <hi>Phaſeoli</hi> come to pay homage to the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Phytognoſtick:</hi> a ſmall one from <hi>Biſnagar,</hi> witha ſhort and knobbed ſolitary Pod, like that of <hi>Orobus;</hi> but covered with a browniſh ſilken Down, whoſe Leaves are of a ſoft and ſilver hue; another from <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deraſpatan,</hi> I whoſe Leaves are ſomewhat like the former; but its Podds are ſmooth, and blackiſh, bloated like a Bladder, with ſeveral Flowers spike faſhion. There is another larger ſort, with many corner'd Leaves, and toberous Root, that's good to eat; which thoſe of <hi>Nevis</hi> call the <hi>Turnep Tree.</hi> Another of this <hi>Batata</hi> kind of <hi>Phaſeole,</hi> from the Southern Cape; a pretty kind of <hi>Phaſeole</hi> with <hi>Laburnum</hi>-Leaves, and ſolitary Flowers, a crooked pod in Figure of a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Cymiter; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with ſuch like Leaves, but a ſmall Melilot, and a ſpiked Flower. A Tree-kind hereof, with Pods no bigger than the ſmalleſt Lentil, and almoſt hid within its <hi>Calyx.</hi> All theſe from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factory of <hi>Fort St. Georgs.</hi> Here is a <hi>Phaſeole,</hi> whoſe Twiggy Stalks are arm'd with Thorns. <hi>Indigenous</hi> of <hi>Japhnapatan;</hi> Two unifoliate Kinds, one from the Eaſt, the other from the Weſtern <hi>Indies,</hi> and very different each from other. Several curious ſorts of <hi>Lycia</hi> and <hi>Rhamni</hi> do here ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the Reader; one Myrtle-leav'd from <hi>Ganges;</hi> and another with a Leaf like <hi>Privet,</hi> from the <hi>Oriental Indies,</hi> that has this Peculiar, of having its Leaf at bottom united to the upper part of the Pedicle, by an Articulation, that makes a pretty Figure of a Navel. The <hi>Saa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouna</hi> of <hi>Piſo</hi> is only here, and no where elſe in Flower.</p>
               <p>A whole Set of Indian <hi>Ricini,</hi> the <hi>Sumach</hi> of <hi>Virginia,</hi> which our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor takes for an <hi>Arbor Copallifera,</hi> among the <hi>Mexicans;</hi> whoſe near, reſemblance to our <hi>Lentiſcus,</hi> gave birth to the Miſtake of thoſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who will needs have our European <hi>Maſtich</hi>-Tree a Native of <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia.</hi> Four ſorts of <hi>Scabious</hi> are all diſplay'd in artificial Sculpture. One from <hi>Biſnagar;</hi> one from <hi>Maderaſpatan;</hi> another from <hi>Jamaica;</hi> and a <hi>Conyzoide</hi> ſort from <hi>Curaſſau.</hi> A <hi>Scorzonera bulboſa</hi> from <hi>Virginia.</hi> The <hi>Stella Orientalis fulgens,</hi> a <hi>Securidaca</hi> kind, from <hi>Maderaſpatan;</hi> and a <hi>Scorpioides</hi> with a ſingle Leaf, from <hi>Biſnagar,</hi> are here laid open to your view.</p>
               <p>You have the <hi>Abſus</hi> of <hi>Alpinus de Pl. Aegypt.</hi> here more Authentick; and the <hi>Mundubi</hi> of the <hi>Braſilians</hi> in <hi>Piſo,</hi> ſo near akin unto it, going hand in hand, with all its Parts, moſt accurately expreſs'd. The <hi>Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtrum</hi>-Family is here enlarged, by the addition of two Biſoliate kinds, from the Coaſt of <hi>Cormandel.</hi> The <hi>Baſella Malabarenſium</hi> in our <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tographia,</hi> in little, is more at large, than in the moſt pompous Picture of it, in the <hi>Hortus Malabaricus,</hi> Part 7. Where neither Berry, nor its
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54947:28"/>Kernel, with its running in a Spiral Line, are in the leaſt taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Tribalus terreſtris,</hi> with a large Poppy-Plower, from the <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Strand,</hi> next offers to divert you; and that other <hi>Ebenus,</hi> the ſame with <hi>Cytiſus Croticus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of <hi>Honerius Belli,</hi> in Leaf ſo like the <hi>Pentaphylloides fruticoſum</hi> of our famous Mr. <hi>Ray,</hi> is no ſmall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament; ſeeing its diverſity from the Trifoliate Kind, is here made obvious. You have here the lively Images of no leſs than two of the <hi>Tulipifera's;</hi> one from <hi>Carolina,</hi> the other from <hi>Virginia,</hi> with Flower and Fruit, both differing from the common Kind. A ſort of <hi>Angelica</hi> from the <hi>Charibbees,</hi> with Seed that taſtes and ſmells of Cummin, and may perhaps be a ſort of <hi>Podagraria.</hi> Very many fine <hi>Apocynums</hi> from the <hi>Weſt-Indies.</hi> A trifoliate <hi>Arum</hi> from <hi>Virginia, Afters</hi> in abundance from all the Quarters of the World; and an <hi>Ophiogloſſum</hi> that ſmells of Musk, with a <hi>Limonium</hi>-Leaf, but not ſo ſtiff, and ſinuate a-top, from the ſame moſt happy Continent of <hi>Virginia.</hi> A <hi>Leonuros</hi> with a white Flower from <hi>America;</hi> and another ſmall purple one, with a ſingle Whortle, or Bout of Flowers crowning its Tops, from <hi>Maderaſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Goat-Balſome</hi>-Tree, from <hi>Antego;</hi> and that other <hi>Babſamiferous</hi> One with a Mulberry-Leaf, call'd the <hi>Baſtard-Cedar,</hi> by our Planters in <hi>Jamaica,</hi> do court your Eye to Recreation; a pair of the new found <hi>Boxekind;</hi> one <hi>African,</hi> and the other <hi>American;</hi> a genuine Branch of the <hi>Canella alba Clus,</hi> or <hi>Caſſia Lignea,</hi> from whence the celebrated <hi>Cortex Winteranus,</hi> together with its Fruit, from the Iſland of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maica,</hi> are well expreſs'd, and happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> preſent themſelves in <hi>Icom.</hi> The <hi>Ceratia diphyllos,</hi> or <hi>Locuſt</hi>-Tree, from <hi>Antego</hi> and <hi>Barbado<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping forth its Soul into a pellucid Reſinous Gum, in Odour of <hi>Olibu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> or our fineſt <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> known by the Name of <hi>Anime;</hi> the ſame with <hi>Piſo</hi>'s <hi>Jetaiba,</hi> with its Branch, its Lobe, and Fruit, is moſt exactly figur'd from the Life; the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngula Gati,</hi> of the <hi>Portugals,</hi> never before in <hi>Icon;</hi> and <hi>Avaremo Temo</hi> of the <hi>Braſilians,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Native of <hi>Bengal,</hi> from whence our Author had it; both in Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with the former, and this, ſo vilely cut in <hi>Piſo</hi> and <hi>Marcgravius,</hi> are here expreſs'd in lively Sculpture. The <hi>Chryſanthemums</hi> are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding new and numerous from ſeveral diſtant Parts of our Terreſtrial Globe. The <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>preſſus Virgintuna Aca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ae foliis,</hi> with its Nots and Fruit; The <hi>Majoran leav'd Clinopodium;</hi> which our Engliſh Planters in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> from its moſt excellent Virtues, diſtinguiſh by the Name of <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany;</hi> and ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Anils</hi> or <hi>Indigoes</hi> from both the <hi>Indies,</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerically
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54947:28"/>differing among themſelves, are here to be found in lively adumbration. Ten of the <hi>Eupat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> Band, Eight <hi>Conyzoide,</hi> and Two of the <hi>Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Order, are here curiouſly exhibited.</p>
               <p>The true <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> a Soliquiferous and Thorny Shrub, the various Kinds of new diſcovered <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> as well Native of <hi>England,</hi> as Exotick; Two <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ories</hi> the one of <hi>Africk,</hi> the other a <hi>Virginiant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> The <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> from the ſame Place: The great Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i, Purſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anes</hi> of ſeveral Sorts from the <hi>Charibbee</hi> Iſlands; and the moſt elegant <hi>Phyllyri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> from <hi>Virginia,</hi> a true <hi>Herba de Raiz;</hi> which by the bended Top-parts of its Leaves, roots in the Ground, and ſo propagates its <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ies,</hi> are all ſurprizing Objects among the Phytographick Tables of our Laborious Author.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o-Scorpiuros,</hi> or <hi>Heliotropium Palmites</hi> from the <hi>Oriental Indies.</hi> The <hi>Rhoi ſimilis Tragodes,</hi> ſmelling ſo like <hi>Androſaemon foetidum,</hi> by thoſe of <hi>Jamaica</hi> call'd <hi>Fing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ego,</hi> and by the <hi>Barbados</hi>-Planters, from its ſtinking ſmell, (as 'tis ſuppoſed,) the <hi>Savin Tree,</hi> is a moſt elegant Shrub, and really deſerves the great Exactneſs that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon its <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> The <hi>Sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſpern</hi> divides into many real and ſpecifick Differences, which with the Baſtard <hi>China,</hi> and True-Born <hi>Sarſaparilla,</hi> are here exhibited with exact Reſemblance to the Life: A <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> from the Kingdom of <hi>Portugal,</hi> with Leaves about a Foot long; a <hi>Virga Aurea</hi> with Leaves, Smell, and Taſte of <hi>Tarracon;</hi> and an <hi>Epidendron,</hi> or <hi>Viſcum arboreum</hi> from the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> with a large white Flower, of admirable Form and Structure, are the Vegetable Wonders that cloſe up this part of the Phytoptical Account: The To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal whereof, muſt needs beſpeak the Author a Perſon of prodigious Pains, and demonſtrate to the World what vaſt Improvements of this Kind might yet further be expected from an Induſtry ſo indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as his.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XII. Praxeos Mayernianae</hi> in Morbis internis, praecipue gravio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, &amp; Chronicis Syntagma, &amp; ex Adverſariis, Conciliis, ac Epiſtolis ejus ſumma Cura ac Diligentia concinnatum. <hi>80.</hi> Lond. <hi>For</hi> Sam. Smith. <hi>1690. pag. 472.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Reputation of the Deceaſed Sir <hi>Theodore Mayern,</hi> is ſo great, and his Cures have prov'd ſo fortunate, That Dr. <hi>De V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ix,</hi> his God Son, could not make a greater Preſent to the Publick, than by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54947:29"/>imparting to it the Remedies which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>maderuſe of with ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n neſs. It were to be wiſh'd, that the Deceaſed Sir <hi>Theodore</hi> had himſelf purſued his own Work, and put in Order; it would have doubtleſs been much more uſeful for our Inſtruction: But in ſhort, ſince all the Remains of Great and Learned Men, are eſteem'd as precious Relicks, there was Reaſon ſufficient for not ſuffering theſe Obſervations, which were found among the Collections of that Famous Phyſician, to be loſt.</p>
               <p>You muſt not expect to meet with many Chymical Remedies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Uſe of ſuch Medicines was but newly begun to be introduc'd in his Time. But there are other Receipts which will appear to be Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the Phyſicians beyond Seal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as, ſeveral Preparations of <hi>Tabacco,</hi> and other Herbs to be ſmoak'd in Pipes, which he preſcrib'd in ſundry Diſtempers: There are ſome Perſons who will hardly believe, that the Smoak of <hi>Tabacco</hi> will reach the Brain; and the Reaſon which they bring for ſo ſaying, is this; becauſe <hi>Tabacco</hi> is an Herb ſo ſharp and vehement, that if the Smoak of it attended and reach'd the Subſtanne of the Brain, it would beget Convulſions in thoſe that took it. But this is no convincing Argument; For beſides the Trouble which they who firſt begin to ſmoak <hi>Tabacco,</hi> have to accuſtome themſelves to take it, and the Noyſomneſs of it to thoſe that love it not, the great Effects which Smoak produces, will doubtleſs prevail with all Perſons not prejudic'd againſt it, to believe that Dr. <hi>Mayern</hi>'s Practice was not without very good Grounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII. Edmundi Richeri</hi> Doctoris Pariſienſis, De Poteſtate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſioe in Rebus Temporalibus, Libri <hi>IV.</hi> Nunquam antehac editi. <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Coloniae;</hi> &amp; <hi>Londini,</hi> for <hi>Abel Swall, 1691. pag. 526.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are few People but have heard of <hi>Richer,</hi> Doctor of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> who has made himſelf ſo famous, for maintaining in Times of Danger and Trouble, the Sovereign Authority of Kings againſt the Uſurpations of the Popes of <hi>Rome.</hi> Theſe Pontiffs always upon the Watch to take the Advantage of all Opportunities, to enlarge their Power, laid hold of the Occaſion which the Minority of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. put into their hands, and the Intrigues of Cardinal <hi>Perron,</hi> who was all in all at that Time in <hi>France,</hi> to ſpread abroad that monſtrous Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their having Power to excommunicate and depoſe Kings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54947:29"/>Clergy was devoted to the Intereſt of the <hi>Roman See;</hi> The Nobility was drawn to their Party by Promiſes and Threats; ſo that the Third Eſtate only ſtood firm; becauſe it was compoſed of Learned <hi>Civilians,</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> well skill'd in the <hi>Canon-Law.</hi> But the Pope's <hi>Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cio</hi> ſo well knew how to ſcare the Queen Regent, the <hi>Chancellor</hi> being beſides, a Penſioner to the Clergy, that he ſilenced the Third Eſtate, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the Publiſhing of the Declaration which was made, and inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theſe Eight Articles.
<list>
                     <item>1.<note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 3.</note> That it ſhould be declared by the Three Eſtates, that the King held his Authority only from God; and that he has no Dependence upon any Authority whatever, either Spiritual or Temporal upon Earth.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2ly,</hi> That all the Subjects in the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> ſhall be obliged without Diſtinction or Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to declare, That this Doctrine is confirm'd by Scripture.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3ly</hi> That the Commiſſioners of the Three Eſtates ſhall ſwear to it, and ſubſcribe it; as likewiſe, all that hold any Office or Benefice.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4ly.</hi> That all the Inſtructers of Youth, Doctors and Preachers ſhall promiſe upon Oath to teach this Doctrine, and refute any Opinion to the contrary, as deteſtable.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5ly.</hi> That all Books which maintain, that it is lawful to excommunicate and depoſe Kings, ſhall be ſuppreſſed as ſeditious.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6ly.</hi> That all Foreigners that ſhall Publiſh the like O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, ſhall be look'd upon as Enemies to the Crown.</item>
                     <item>7. That all the King's Subjects who declare themſelves to be of their Opinions, ſhall be proceeded againſt as guilty of High Treaſon.</item>
                     <item>8. That if any Religious Foreigner ſhall maintain any Propoſition contrary to the Law of the States of the Kingdom, thoſe of the ſame Order in <hi>France,</hi> ſhall be obliged to condemn it ſolemnly, and without Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; as alſo to refute the Author, if it be thought neceſſary.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>C.l. You will find more at large the Hiſtory of all theſe Diſputes in the Firſt Chapter of the Firſt Book of this Work. In the Second Chapter the Author ſhews, That the Practice of the Catholick Church is conformable to the Declaration of the Third Eſtate. In the Third, he proves, That it is no leſs conformable to the Practice &amp; Doctrine of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, which has all along defended the Authority of Kings againſt the Uſurpations of the Popes, with an extraordinary Zeal; for which the Author brings many Examples,<note n="(b)" place="margin">p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Hinkmar</hi> the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Rhemes</hi>'s Letter to Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the Second.</item>
                     <item>2. The Refuſal of the French Clergy to obey <hi>Gregory</hi> VII. who would forbid the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating of Divine Offices in <hi>France.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The Anſwer which the Miniſters of <hi>Philip Aug.</hi> gave to the Legat of <hi>Innocent</hi> III. who would have excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54947:30"/>
                        <hi>Lewis</hi> VIII. <hi>Philip</hi>'s Eldeſt Son, becauſe he had taken Arms to maintain the Right, which the Election of the Barons of <hi>England,</hi> (revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from K. <hi>John,</hi> for ſubmitting himſelf a Vaſſal to the Pope,) gave him to the Crown of that Kingdom.</item>
                     <item>4. The Conſtancy of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> who would never yield to his Clergy, That their Excommunications were of any force, till they were examin'd and confirm'd by the Secular Magiſtrate.</item>
                     <item>5. The Acts of the Three Eſtates againſt <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII. which conſtrained his Succeſſor <hi>Clement.</hi> V. to revoke his extravagant <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nam Sanctam.</hi> To this, the Author adds the Decrees of Parliament againſt the Books of <hi>John Tanquarelli, Bernardin Caſtori,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuits, Decanus, Suarez</hi> and others who advanc'd the Power of the Popes above that of Kings.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. In the Second Book, the Author marks out the Method which he intends to obſerve; and ſets down Three General Heads,<note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 66.</note> by which we are to examin whether a Doctrine be Orthodox or no.
<list>
                     <item>1. He would have it ſo clearly contain'd in Scripture, that it may be clearly drawn from thence without any tedious Ratiocinations.</item>
                     <item>2. If the Senſe of the Paſſage be conteſted, to have recourſe to the Tradition of the Church, that is to ſay, to the unanimous Opinion of the Ancient Fathers.</item>
                     <item>3. To aſſure your ſelves that this Tradition is true, and that it proves ſomething, it is requiſite that it ſhould be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal; that is to ſay, receiv'd &amp; believ'd in all Times, and in all Places.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Afterwards the Author examines a little Scholaſtically, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs with good Judgment, the Eſſential and Formal Cauſes of Politick Power. There he makes an <hi>Analyſis</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">p 73.</note> of that famous Paſſage of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2. and ſhews that the moſt Learned of the Fathers, <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an, Origen,</hi> St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> &amp;c. and the moſt Famous Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Doctors, <hi>Tho. Aquinas, Tolletus, Estius, Cornelius à Lapide,</hi> &amp;c. believed that that ſame Paſſage prov'd the Independency of Princes from all other humane Authority. He proves the ſame Thing,<note n="(c)" place="margin">p. 109.</note> by the Commentaries of the Ancients upon the Words of <hi>David,</hi> Pſal-50. <hi>Againſt Thee only have I ſinned.</hi> He examines the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Moſaick Prieſthood and the Goſpel, and ſhews, that though Princes were to ſubmit to the Prieſts in Spiritual Things, it did not follow, that they had any Superiour in Temporals.</p>
               <p>After he has confirm'd his Opinion by the Canons of ſeveral Councils, and given Examples of the Fidelity of the <hi>French</hi> to their Princes,<note n="(d)" place="margin">p. 123.</note> before they were corrupted by the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> he examines the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether it be lawful for the People to depoſe Princes? and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54947:30"/>thoſe that hold the Affirmative. The Reaſons which he alledges,<note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 133.</note> amount to this, That the Publick Good, Peace, and Repoſe of Society, are of Divine Right; whence it follows,
<list>
                     <item>1. That it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to prejudice or diſturb them.</item>
                     <item>2. That Religion cannot be a juſt Pretence to take Arms, ſince War can only pretend to regulate the Temporalty.</item>
                     <item>3. That in Moral Things, that which cannot be obtain'd but with extream difficulty, and a very great and inevitable danger, is look'd upon as an Impoſſibility; and therefore it is better to bear with a Tyrant, than to expoſe Society to be turn'd Topſie Turvy, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to take him out of the World.</item>
                     <item>4. That the Maxim, That no Faith is to be obſerv'd with him that has violated his own, takes no place in Publick Contracts, where the Intereſt of the whole Society is concern'd.</item>
                     <item>5. That it only appertains to Sovereigns to make War; becauſe they have no other way to preſerve their Rights, and prevent the Subverſion of their Dominions.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>After this, the Author anſwers the Objection drawn from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> and examines the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of <hi>M. Antonius de Dominis,</hi> who maintains, That Kings are immediately eſtabliſhed by God; whereas our Author pretends, that it is the Society that has Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority, and communicates it to thoſe into whoſe Hands the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety commits the Sovereign Power.</p>
               <p n="3">III. In the Two following Books, the Author treats of the Nature of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Power;</hi> and ſhews,<note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 162.</note> That it has no other Aim, but to remove the Clergy from the World, and oblige them only to mind the Salvation of Souls.
<list>
                     <item>2. That the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> did not ſucceed Jeſus Chriſt in the quality of Governor of the Univerſe; but only as Miniſters, and Preachers of the Goſpel.</item>
                     <item>3. That <hi>Excommunication</hi> is a cutting off from the Communion of the Church; and that it does not deprive thoſe that are ſmitten with it, of their Natural and Civil Rights; and that it is of no force, unleſs it be pronounced with the Conſent of the whole Church.</item>
                     <item>4. That when the Publick Tranquillity is concern'd, the Magiſtrate has a Right to take Cognizance of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Cenſures.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In the Fifth Chapter, the Author examines the Errors of <hi>Marſilius</hi> of <hi>Padua,</hi> and <hi>John Duns,</hi> which Pope <hi>John</hi> XXII. condemn'd in the Year 1320, (<hi>p.</hi> 323.) The Bull reduces theſe pretended Errors to Five Heads.
<list>
                     <item>1. That when Jeſus Chriſt paid Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> he did not pay him out of a bare Submiſſion; but through the Neceſſity of the Obligation he was in, as he was a Man, to obey Superiour Powers.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:54947:31"/>2. That St. <hi>Peter</hi> had no more Authority, nor was any more the Head of the Church than the reſt of the Apoſtles. That Jeſus Chriſt did not eſtabliſh any viſible Head, or leave any ſuch Vicar as the Pope.</item>
                     <item>3. That the Emperor has a Right to eſtabliſh, correct and puniſh, nay, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Pope.</item>
                     <item>4. That all Miniſters of the Goſpel are equal by the Inſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt; and that the Difference which is between them, is only founded upon the Conceſſions of Princes, and may be revok'd.</item>
                     <item>5. That neither the Pope, nor the whole Body of the Church have any Right to puniſh Criminals, farther than Sovereigns give them Authority.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In the Eighth Chapter, Monſieur <hi>Richer</hi> treats of the Immunities of the Clergy, and refutes the Arguments of <hi>Suarez</hi> and <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> who affirm, That the Pope has a Right to exempt Eccleſiaſtical Perſons from the Civil Juriſdiction without the Conſent of the Emperor, or any other Sovereign Princes.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. In the Firſt Chapter of the Fourth Book, the Author ſets down a Hiſtory of <hi>Inveſtitures,</hi> or the Collation of <hi>Benefices.</hi> He ſhews how the Election of <hi>Paſtors</hi> paſs'd from the People to Kings, and the great ſtruglings of the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> to make themſelves Maſters of it.</p>
               <p>In the Second Chapter, he anſwers the Arguments of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Baronius,</hi> againſt <hi>Secular Inveſtitures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Third and laſt Chapter contains the Hiſtory of <hi>Gregory</hi> VII. the firſt who uſurp'd to himſelf the Power of depoſing Kings, and firſt preſum'd to put this pretended. Power in execution. The Author gives himſelf the trouble to anſwer the Arguments which that unworthy Pontiff alledges, for advancing himſelf above God's Vicegerents on Earth; according to the Prediction of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. We ſhall mention only one; becauſe it ſhews the <hi>Genius</hi> of that Pope, and the Eſteem which Popes, like him, have of Crowned Heads. To prove that the Church is above Kings, obſerve how he argues. Royal Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was invented by Seculars who knew not God, but by the inſtigation of their Prince the Devil, <hi>Principe Diabolo agitante,</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 482.</note> whereas the Eccleſiaſtick Power was inſtituted by the Providence of God, and and aims at his Glory. Therefore as much as God is above the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:54947:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XIV. Analyſis Aequationum Univerſalis,</hi> &amp;c. An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis</hi> of Equations; <hi>Or,</hi> A Short and General Method of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving <hi>Algebraical Equations;</hi> deduc'd and demonſtrated out of the New Doctrine of <hi>Infinite Series:</hi> By <hi>JOSEPH RAPHSON,</hi> Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Swall, 1690. pag. 50.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE are in a manner indebted to Chance for the compoſing of this little Treatiſe, ſince Mr. <hi>Raphſon,</hi> the ingenious Author thereof, accidentally invented this Method, on the Occaſion of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem that had been propounded to him by one of his Friends. For he declares, that he never ſaw any thing of the like Nature: And indeed, the Novelty of the Subject might be alone ſufficient to recommend it to the World; and to induce the Author to appropriate to himſelf the ſole Reputation of ſo conſiderable an Invention, were he not preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his innate Modeſty, and the little regard that he hath for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Applauſe. However, we ſhall leave it to thoſe that are skilful in thoſe Matters, to determine, whether any thing hath been hitherto Publiſh'd, tending to the ſame effect; and in caſe there hath, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it cannot be imagin'd but that they will readily allow the juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation that is due to this worthy Member of the <hi>Royal Society;</hi> for it is not to be admir'd, that Learned Men have often like Notions and Sentiments with reſpect to the ſame Subject.</p>
               <p>Moreover, Mr. <hi>Raphſon</hi> explains his<note n="(a)" place="margin">1.</note> Method after the very ſame manner as he invented it, and to ſhew the large Extent and Certainty thereof, he propounds a general<note n="(b)" place="margin">3.</note> Theorem, which he afterwards reſolves more particularly in Two Propoſitions: Then he proceeds to illuſtrate his Method by Examples,<note n="(c)" place="margin">5.</note> in 32 Problems; wherein is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited the Reſolution of Equations, of all manner of Dimenſions, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Reſolution of a Simple Equation: Whereunto he adds Examples of Quadratick Equations, All his Operations are deſcribed at large; and to render the Practice more plain and obvious, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath taken the Pains to compoſe certain Tables, which are inſerted at the End; inſomuch that if he continue to proſecute theſe Studies, as he hath begun, it is not to be doubted but that he will become one of the moſt skilful <hi>Mathematicians</hi> that are now living; ſince at the Age of 22 Years, he hath already attained to ſo great a Knowledge in thoſe abſtruſe and difficult Sciences: Wherefore what improvement may we not expect from the extraordinary Judgment of his riper Years?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:54947:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XV. Curſus Mathematicus:</hi> Mathematical Sciences; in Nine Books: Comprehending <hi>Arithmetick</hi> Vulgar, Decimal, Inſtrumental, Algebraical; <hi>Geometry,</hi> Plain and Solid; <hi>Coſmography,</hi> Celeſtial and Terreſtrial; <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> Theorical and Practical; <hi>Navigation,</hi> Plain and Spherical; <hi>Trigonometry,</hi> Rectilinear and Circular: With the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, Conſtruction and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Geometrical and Nautical Inſtruments, and the <hi>Doctrine of Triangles,</hi> applyed to Practiſe in Menſurations of all kinds; as <hi>in Longimetry,</hi> or taking of Heights, Diſtances, <hi>&amp;c. Planome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> or Surveying of Lands, Woods, Roads, <hi>&amp;c. Military Architecture,</hi> or <hi>Fortification;</hi> and in <hi>Navigation, Dyalling,</hi> &amp;c. All which are diſpos'd in ſuch a Method as they ought to be read and practis'd by ſuch as would attain to a competent Perfictency in them by their own Industry. By <hi>William Leybourn, Philomathes,</hi> in Fol. <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>Benjamin</hi> Took, <hi>&amp;c. 1690. p. 984.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is not at all to be wondred, that the Body of this Work does not perfectly anſwer to the Title: For that the <hi>Mathematicks</hi> are of ſo vaſt an Extent, that it is impoſſible to include them all in one ſingle Volume; therefore how careful ſoever Mr. <hi>Leybourn</hi> has been to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, he could not treat in this Volume of <hi>Mechanicks, Civil Archite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, Conick Sections, Muſick, Opticks, Diopticks,</hi> and the Parts that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them, and which he ſeems to reſerve for a Second Part.</p>
               <p>Now in regard the Title of this Book ſufficiently ſhews what it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and that we cannot diſcourſe of all the Matters therein contain'd, we ſhall only give you here the Extract of one ſingle Treatiſe, to ſhew the Author's Method. And we have made choice of that of <hi>Navigation,</hi> becauſe we thought it would be moſt delightful to a Nation ſo much concern'd to be perfect in the Knowledge of it.</p>
               <p>'Tis in the Seventh Book, that Mr. <hi>Leybourn</hi> undertakes to unfold the Art of <hi>Navigation.</hi> In the Preface,<note n="(a)" place="margin">p 605.</note> he aſcribes the Invention of it to God only, and not to the <hi>Egyptians</hi> or <hi>Phoenicians,</hi> as ſome Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors do; for that it was God who firſt diſcoverd to <hi>Noah</hi> the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Ships and Navigation, in the Time of the Deluge; and for that it was according to the Model of the Ark, which reſted upon the Mountains of <hi>Ararat,</hi> that the Neighbouring Nations built their Ships.</p>
               <p>The Body of the Work is divided into Four Parts. The Firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains five Chapters, which are ſubdivided into Sections, when the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter requires it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:54947:32"/>In the Firſt Chapter,<note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 106.</note> the Author ſpeaks of Navigation in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; the Rules of which are only to furniſh a Pilot with the ſafeſt ways to ſteer a Veſſel whither he deſigns it. To which purpoſe, he muſt have a regard to four Things; the <hi>Longitude,</hi> the <hi>Latitude,</hi> the <hi>Courſe,</hi> and the <hi>Diſtance.</hi> They who are but never ſo little vers'd in the Sphere, know what the Longitude is: But the moſt Judicious are ſtill igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Secret, how to find it exactly upon the Sea. There is not the ſame Ignorance about the Latitude; for there are ſeveral Ways to know it; either by the Meridional Heights of the Sun, or by ſome known Star, by the riſing and ſetting Amplitudes, or by the Pole-Star. If Mariners could find the Longitude as well, they would have all that they ſeek for: But in regard we have but an imperfect Knowledge of the Longitude, we are oblig'd to have recourſe to the Ship's Way, and the Diſtance of the Veſſel; but more eſpecially to the Latitudes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the moſt exactly that may be, the Place where it is. The Ship's Courſe is the Way which it ſteers upon the Sea; which is eaſily known by the Compaſs or Needle, great Care being taken to obſerve its Variation. As for the Diſtance, which is the Length of the Way which the Veſſel makes, it is not ſo eaſie to conclude it: But this is the way to take it; They let down into the Sea a Plummet of Lead fix'd to a Line, and at the ſame time they turn an Hour-Glaſs; then they obſerve what quantity of Line the Log-Line draws out of the Veſſel, thereby to know how much way the Veſſel makes in ſuch a prefix'd time, with the ſame Wind, and the ſame Number of Sails. But there are ſeveral Inconveniences in this way of Practice; ſo that there is no building upon it: For it is not certain that the Log-Line ſtays in the ſame place where it was thrown:
<list>
                     <item>1. By reaſon of the Toſſing of the Waves, eſpecially in a rough Sea.</item>
                     <item>2. The Wind does not always blow alike, and it is a hard thing to meaſure the Briskneſs of a Gale.</item>
                     <item>3. The Toſſing and Shogging of the Ship will not let the Hour-Glaſſes which they make uſe of to meaſure the Time, run ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly true.</item>
                     <item>4. The ſtrong Currents which are met with in certain places, may occaſion Miſtake in the knowledge of Diſtances; ſo that you muſt endeavour to diſcover them by their Strength, their Rapid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and their Courſe.</item>
                  </list> But you may in ſome meaſure attain your Ends, if inſtead of the Log-line, you make uſe of a piece of Wood, or a ſmall Bucket, with a piece of Lead fix'd to it, to make it ſink into the Sea about 60 or 80 Fathom: For then by obſerving the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Line, the Sand, and the Compaſs, you may in a great meaſure avoid the Miſtakes which the Currents may occaſion in the Diſtances.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54947:33"/>Now ſuppoſe that you know the Diſtances in Feet, or in Miles, and the Rumb, or Courſe of the Veſſel, it is eaſie to obſerve the Point, and under what Degree you are, provided you know the Latitude of the Place from whence you ſet Sail, and where you are, and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miles and Feet there are in a Degree. The Author tells you, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Mr. <hi>Richard Norwood,</hi> that there are in a Degree 367200 Feet: But for the eaſineſs of Calculation, and becauſe it is better to ſuppoſe that there are leſs than more, he allows but 360000 Feet to a Degree.</p>
               <p>C. 2. After this,<note n="(c)" place="margin">p. 600, 617.</note> he diſcourſes of the Inſtruments made uſe of in Navigation, as well for making Obſervations, as for the Eaſineſs of Operations. He gives you the Deſcription, and ſets down the Uſe of them. The Inſtruments are, The <hi>Plain Compaſs,</hi> the <hi>Azimuth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Ring-Dial,</hi> the <hi>Croſs Staff,</hi> or <hi>Fore-Staff,</hi> the <hi>Quadrant,</hi> or <hi>Back-Staff,</hi> and the <hi>Nocturnal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>C. 3. He ſhews<note n="(d)" place="margin">p. 618.</note> the manner of finding out the Latitudes; and in the following Chapter,<note n="(e)" place="margin">p. 621.</note> he treats of the vulgar Notes of the <hi>Julian</hi> Year, of the Motion of the Sun and Moon, and gives ſome ſhort Rules to find them at any time; explaining afterwards their great Uſe in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation.</p>
               <p>C. 5. In regard the knowledge of the Tides is very uſeful to a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot,<note n="(f)" place="margin">p. 633</note> the Author, in the laſt Chapter, gives you Tables, and ſets down Rules how to know them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Part</hi> 2. In the Second Part<note n="(g)" place="margin">p. 634.</note> he diſcourſes of <hi>Plain Sayling,</hi> and puts in practice the Doctrine of <hi>Rectilineal Triangles,</hi> for the Solution of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Nautical Problems and Queſtions in <hi>Plain Sayling;</hi> all which are performed with Scale and Compaſſes, by Trigonometrical Calculation,<note n="(h)" place="margin">p. 646</note> either by Tables, or Proportional Scales, or wrought upon the Chart it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Part</hi> 3. After this,<note n="(i)" place="margin">p. 656.</note> Mr. <hi>Leybourn</hi> proceeds to the Third Part; where he explains Mr. <hi>Wright</hi>'s Method, vulgarly call'd <hi>Mercator's Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;</hi> and he applies to practice the Doctrine of <hi>Rectilineal Triangles,</hi> with the Supply of <hi>Meridional Parts,</hi> in the Solution of Nautical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems in Sayling by the true Sea-Chart; and all this is performed by <hi>Protraction,</hi> by <hi>Calculation,</hi> and upon the <hi>Chart</hi> it ſelf. There is alſo a Parallel between the Plain and the true <hi>Sea Chart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:54947:33"/>P. 4.<note n="(k)" place="margin">p. 667, 672.</note> As the Method call'd <hi>Mercator</hi>'s Sayling ſurpaſſes the Plain Sayling; ſo that which is ſet forth in this Fourth Part, and is call'd <hi>Circular Sayling,</hi> ſurpaſſes the other two Methods. He therefore reſolves by Trigonometry, and the Projections of the Sphear, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems of Sayling by the Arch of a Great Circle. After which, you ſhall meet with ſome Tables, the Uſe of which is very frequent in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation. The Tables bear the Title of <hi>Calendarium Nauticum,</hi> and <hi>Aſtrale Calendarium.</hi> There are alſo ſome other Tables in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and quite through the whole Body of the Work, where they are neceſſary to be inſerted. Neither has he forgot to add the famous Tables of <hi>Logarithms,</hi> of <hi>Sinus</hi> and <hi>Tangents,</hi> &amp;c. He has alſo taken care to cauſe ſuch Figures as the Diſcourſe requires, to be neatly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven upon Copper Plates, and placed at the End of the Book for the Conveniency of the Readers.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Letter of the Honourable Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> to the Author of this Hiſtory of Learning.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Here ſend you an Experiment which made a great Noiſe In the Court of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and which will reſolve all the Difficulties in the Queſtions which you propos'd to me, concerning the Coldneſs of Water. It was made by a Captain of a Ship, a Man of very good Senſe, and in the Preſence of a great many Perſons; inſomuch that there can be no manner of Doubt concerning it.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:54947:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> An Account of ſome Obſervations made in the great Congregation of Waters, by lowering Bottles down into the Sea ſix hundred Foot deep from the Surface, <hi>January</hi> 2d. <hi>1677/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Day, in the Lat. of 36 d. and 40 m. about 30 Leagues diſtant from <hi>Cape St. Vincent,</hi> it bearing from us E. N. E. having receiv'd ſome Command from the right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> concerning making Experiments in this Nature, we lay by with our Frigot, the St. <hi>David,</hi> whilſt Sir <hi>Richard Munden,</hi> with ſome other Gentlemen, was pleas'd to go along with me in the Pinnace, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Trial of theſe Experiments.</p>
               <p>And having made faſt to a deep ſide Lead and Line, one Vial-Glaſs fill'd with the Oil of Aniſeeds, according to Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s Direction, to experiment the Coldneſs of the Deeps below; as alſo two ordinary Bottles only fill'd with Air, the one being firmly clos'd with a ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Cork, and the other with Wood, being all ſecurely made faſt, We lowered them down into Eight Fathom, and there remained fifteen Minutes; then haled them aloft to the Surface of the Waters. The Oil of Aniſeed was congealed and curdled; which demonſtrates the Coldneſs of thoſe Regions below; the Cork-Stopple was ſuck'd into the Bottle; but that cloſed with Wood, remained as at the firſt; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through its Pores was forceably drawn in, about half the Stowage of the Bottle, with Salt Water; which boiling out from the little Crannies of the Wood, after haling the Stopple out, the Salt-Water <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moak'd, as though it had been ſome ſtrong Liquor, or Spirit.</p>
               <p>Upon the Second Experiment, I ſeized faſt, three Bottles to the deep-ſide Line a little above the Lead; two of them were firmly cloſed with Stopples made of a light ſort of <hi>Lignum Vitae,</hi> which my Lord Treaſurer propoſed; the other, with a firm Cork; then lowered them into one hundred Fathom depth: And having remained there about five Minutes, I perceived upon the Surface of the Water the two <hi>Lignum Vitae</hi> Stopples; wondering at the Cauſe, I immediately haled up the Lead, and the Bottles were ſtaved in many pieces, either by the weight of the Water, or condenſing of the Air, that remained within them. The other Bottle, only clos'd with a Cork-Stopple, was ſuck'd in, and ſo fill'd full of Water, (probably near the depth of one hundred Fathom;) and being curious to taſte thereof, it was not only my Opinion, but all the reſt of the Gentlemen in the Pinnace
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54947:34"/>with me, That this Water was much freſher than that we taſted upon the Surface. I ſhall proceed the firſt convenient opportunity, as near as poſſible I can, by Experience and Demonſtration, to reſolve the great Enquiries concerning the Current of the <hi>Streights Mouth</hi> of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braltar.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>XVIII. Inſcriptionum Antiquarum Sylloge, <hi>in duas Partes diſtributa; in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſum Jnventut is Rerum Antiquarum ſtudioſae edita; &amp; Notis illuſtrata; à</hi> Guliel. Fleetwood, <hi>Col. Regal. apud</hi> Cantab. <hi>Socio.</hi> Octav. <hi>Londini,</hi> apud <hi>Tim Child,</hi> 1691. p. 572. A Collection of Ancient Inſcriptions; Divided into Two Parts.</head>
               <p>Inſcriptions being a great help to Hiſtory, and Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> having often obſerved, that the reaſon why the Study of them was not ſo frequent, was, becauſe it required the turning over of a great number of Volumes, where they were diſpers'd up and down; which it would coſt a great deal of Time and Money to do; he thought fit to do the Publick an acceptable piece of Service, by collecting the moſt remarkable, and ſuch as are moſt uſeful to clear the Obſcurity of ancient Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</p>
               <p>In the Firſt Part, the Author has very nearly obſerv'd <hi>Gruterus</hi> his Method: And ſo it is divided into Five Parts. Of which, the Firſt,<note n="(a)" place="margin">p. 1.</note> includes the Inſcriptions relating to Pagan Divinities. The Second,<note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 53.</note> Thoſe which concern publick Monuments. The Third,<note n="(c)" place="margin">p. 92.</note> Thoſe which were made for the Emperors. The Fourth,<note n="(d)" place="margin">p. 130.</note> Thoſe which are to be read upon the Tombs or Statues of them that officiated at the Altars of the Magiſtrates, and other Publick Perſons. The Fifth,<note n="(e)" place="margin">p. 171.</note> contains the Epitaphs which Fathers, Mothers, and Children, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and Wives, Servants and Maſters, Kindred and Friends made upon one another.</p>
               <p>The Second includes all the Chriſtian Epitaphs, Inſcriptions, and other Monuments that are extant, or at leaſt, that are printed till the Ninth or Tenth Age. The Author has profitably made uſe of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54947:35"/>Words of <hi>Arcudius, Aringhus, Reineſius, Spon,</hi> the Travels of <hi>Whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> and the Fathers <hi>Mabillon</hi> and <hi>Germain;</hi> though ſometimes he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears not to refute them in his Notes. There are ſome which are no leſs profitable than learned; as that,<note n="(f)" place="margin">p. 40.2.</note> where he ſhews, that St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> was miſtaken in taking a ſuppoſed Inſcription, for that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> alledges to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> Acts 18.23. Such are alſo the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks which are made upon the Inſcriptions,<note n="(g)" place="margin">p. 115.</note> where they give to <hi>Diocleſian</hi> the honour of having aboliſhed the Chriſtian Name, with as much truth as the Flatterers of <hi>Lewis</hi> X V. endeavour to perſuade him that he has triumphed over all <hi>Europe,</hi> and aboliſh'd the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
               <p>There is one Inſcription in Verſe,<note n="(h)" place="margin">p. 379.2.</note> upon the Roof of the Church of St. <hi>Agnes,</hi> in the Suburbs of <hi>Rome. Baronius</hi> pretends that that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription was put there by <hi>Conſtantina,</hi> the Daughter of the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour, for having recovered her Health through the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of that Saint, over whoſe Sepulchre ſhe cauſe that Church to be built; and after that vow'd perpetual Virginity. This Story being very improbable, had need of credible Vouchers: In the mean time, it is only founded upon the Teſtimony of Modern Authors, and thoſe <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> On the other ſide, it is certain, that <hi>Conſtantina</hi> was twice Married: Whence Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> concludes, That the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantina</hi> mentioned in the Inſcription, was ſome other than the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's Daughter, and that ſhe could not be living till toward the End of the Fifth Age; ſince <hi>Prudentius,</hi> an Author of the Fifth Century, and who ſpeaks of the Sepulchre of St. <hi>Agnes,</hi> makes no mention of this Church.</p>
               <p>Now in regard there are no Paſſions more eloquent than <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Grief;</hi> there are ſome of theſe Epitaphs which are Maſter-pieces in their kind: Such is that,<note n="(i)" place="margin">p. 193.</note> which <hi>Atimetus,</hi> the Emperour <hi>Titus</hi>'s enfranchiz'd Bond man caus'd to be engraven upon his Wives Urn. And that other,<note n="(k)" place="margin">p. 535.</note> which is between his Collection of Chriſtian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, whoſe Authors are unknown; where a Mother that had loſt her Children, is made to ſpeak.</p>
               <p>We ſhould here finiſh this Extract, were we not to obſerve in the Author's Epiſtle Dedicatory,<note n="(m)" place="margin">p. 3.</note> one Scruple which a Chriſtian Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher cannot let paſs without an Anſwer. If it be true, ſaith he, that Reaſon convinces us of the Unity of a God; how is it poſſible that the Pagans, who were Rational Men, adored ſeveral? It follows of neceſſity, that either they ador'd one and the ſame God under ſeveral Names, and conſequently, that they were not guilty of Idolatry; or
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:54947:35"/>elſe that Reaſon is not now adays the ſame as it was formerly, and ſo there is no certainty; or at leaſt that Men did not make a right uſe of their Reaſon for ſo many Ages.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> aſſerts that it is the ſame<note n="*">Si a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a erat illorum ratio à noſtra, vel (quod idem eſt) ſi aliter ratione ſua uſi ſunt homines, ubinam quaeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, iſta adeò jactain Ration<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s certitudo, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, per tot ſecula, omnes ferè via recta aberraverint?</note> thing to have a Reaſon different from ours, and to make uſe of it in another manner. But I am not of his Opinion: For it is demonſtrable, that Colours, Heat and Cold, are not in the Objects that produce thoſe different Senſes of Feeling in us. Nevertheleſs, 'tis but within theſe few Years, that a ſmall number of Philoſophers have retriev'd themſelves from this Miſtake: All the reſt of Mankind is ſtill in that Errour; and it may be there are above Three Fourths of the World that will never be undeceived. Tell a Country man, that Fire is not hot, Ice not cold, and Snow not white, he will deride your Simplicity; and if he thought it concerned his Temporal or Eternal Intereſt, to defend the contrary, you might expect for want of Proofs, to be treated by him as the Pagans treated the Chriſtians, or as the Papiſts treat the Proteſtants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To prove that there is but one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Infinite Being, and that none ought to pay any Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to Creatures, let them be never ſo excellent, you muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Reaſons much more abſtracted, than thoſe that demonſtrate, That Colours are not in the Bodies which affect our Senſes. The Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion is the moſt perfect &amp; ſublime of all Philoſophies; whence it comes to paſs, that ſo few People underſtand it throughly, and that to ſupply the defect of Attention and Meditation among the greateſt part of Men; the Scripture ſo often commands us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. If we made a right uſe of Reaſon, Faith would not be ſo neceſſary, but only for Matters of Fact, which are contain'd in the Sacred Letters, and which have all the Certainty that Hiſtories can be capable of. But leaving here a Reflexion which would carry us a great way farther, we ſhall conclude with this Obſervation, That this Objection, which ſeems at firſt ſo formidable, is grounded only upon the equivocal ſignification of a Word. For in common Speech, <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſignifies both the Light of Nature, and the manner of thinking. In the firſt Sence, Reaſon is an infallible Guide which never leaves thoſe that follow it, into Errour. But in the ſecond Senſe, it may be ſaid, that Reaſon miſguides and deceives us, becauſe it happens too frequently, that Men determine themſelves, without conſulting the inward Light, and the eternal Reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:54947:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> The Falſhood of Humane Vertue, done out of <hi>French, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> London, <hi>For</hi> Tim. Child, <hi>p. 308.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOnſieur <hi>Eſprit,</hi> of the French Academy, propoſes to himſelf, to prove in this Work, That all the Vertues of Men, conſidered in the corrupted State of Nature, have no other Foundation but Self-Love; not excepting the moſt glorious and beautiful; as, <hi>Prudence, Sincerity, Friendſhip, Clemency, Compaſſion, Generoſity;</hi> nor even thoſe that ſeem to approach the neareſt to Chriſtian Vertues; as, <hi>Humility, Liberality, Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Integrity.</hi> This is that which he does in 21 Chapters; which are ſo many Rhetorical Diſcourſes upon every one of the Humane Vertues. There he ſometimes handles Queſtions very material; as in the 19th. Chapter, where ſpeaking of the Fidelity of Subjects toward their Sovereigns, he enquires, <hi>What is the Duty of Subjects, when Kings violate the Fundamental Law of the Kingdom?</hi> And after he has produced the Anſwers of ſundry Politicians, and ſhewn, that their Reaſoning engages them in Difficulties, from whence they cannot diſintangle themſelves, he concludes, That the beſt courſe a Man can take, not only for the Peace of his Conſcience, but alſo in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a quiet Life, is not to meddle at all with Affairs of State, when he has no Call to the Government. For Liberty, and the Eaſe of the People, are loud Words which the Factious make uſe of, but that ſignifie nothing in their Mouths; they always found it miſchievous who believ'd 'em; and the Diſorder muſt be very great indeed, if a Civil War be not a Remedy worſe than the Diſeaſe. As for <hi>Religion,</hi> the Author maintains. That how ſpecious ſoever the Pretence may be, 'tis no better than that of Taxes and Impoſts: That the Seditious, who make the moſt of this Argument, are they who have the leaſt value for it; that it is well known that the Heads of the League againſt the Kings of <hi>France, Hen.</hi> 3. and <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. made uſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> as a Cloak to cover their ambitious Deſigns; and that it is better to follow the Example of the Primitive Chriſtians, who during the firſt Four Ages, obey'd the Pagan Emperours, without murmuring and reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:54947:36"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Books lately Printed in Foreign Parts; to be Sold by <hi>Abel Swall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Timothy Childe</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn in</hi> St <hi>Paul's</hi> Church Yard.</head>
            <p>Some whereof were deſigned to have been inſerted in this Journal; but we wanting room, have deferr'd it till the next, when they ſhall be more ſully deſcrib'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SAncti Caecil. Cypriani</hi> Opera omnia, Recognita &amp; Illuſtrata per <hi>Joan. Oxonienſ.</hi> Epiſc. Accedunt Annales Cypriani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; five XIII. Annorum quibus <hi>S. Cyprianus</hi> inter Chriſtianos verſatus eſt, Brevis Chronologice delineate, per <hi>Joan. Ceſtrienſem.</hi> Huic Editioni annexae ſunt Diſſertationes Cyprianicae, ab <hi>Henrico Dodwello. Juxta Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar Oxonii à Theatro.</hi> Amſt. 1691. Folio.</p>
            <p>Though this Book is very much known to the Learned, yet we have reſolv'd to give a large Account of it in the next Journal: The Writings of that Father being one of the moſt Venerable Monuments of Antiquity, and his two Commentators, Dr. <hi>Pearſon,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Fell,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> two of the moſt Learned Men of this Age; to ſay nothing of Mr. <hi>Dodwell;</hi> ſince he being yet alive, it would look too much like Flattery. We ſhall only now add, that this Edition is very well Printed in a fair Character and Paper, and with the Addition of Mr. <hi>Dodwell</hi>'s Diſſertations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phil. à Limborch</hi> de Veritate Religionis Chriſtianae, Amica Collatio cum Erudito Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeo. <hi>Amſt.</hi> 1691. in Quarto.</p>
            <p>This Book contains ſome Conferences between a <hi>Jew,</hi> Doctor of Phyſick at <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> who died there ſome Years ago; and the Ingenious <hi>Philip van Limborch,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor or Divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity amongſt the <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inians</hi> at the ſame City; and is an excellent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Chriſtian Faith, anſwering all the moſt ſpecious Arguments of the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt it. But there being ſeveral things relating to both the Authors, and the Boak wherewith the World is not acquainted, it is thought fit to defer till our next, to give an Account thereof,</p>
            <p>Ejuſdem <hi>Phil. à Limborch</hi> Theologia Chriſtiana ad Praxin Pietatis ac Promotionem Pacis Chriſtianae unice; directa: <hi>Amſt.</hi> in Quarto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lud. Ellies du Pin</hi> de Antiqua Eccleſiae Diſciplina Diſſertationes Hiſtoricae, excerptae ex Conciliis Oecumenicis, &amp; Sanctorum Patrum ac Actorum Eccleſiaſticorum Scriptis. Quarto. <hi>Amſt.</hi> 1691.</p>
            <p>Whatever hath relation to the Primitive Ages of Chriſtianity, is ſo much look'd upon by the Engliſh Divines, and Dr. <hi>du Pin,</hi> though a Roman Catholick, is ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial a Perſon, that we believe they will be well pleaſed to find an Abſtract of it in our next.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joan. Spencer,</hi> de Legibus Hebraeorum Ritualibus, &amp; carum Rationibus; Editio ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda, priori Indice Locorum S. Script locupletiore, necnon Indice Rerum &amp; Verborum memorabilium novo aucta. in Quarto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lud. Thomaſini</hi> Vetus &amp; Nova Eccleſiae Diſciplina, circa Beneficia &amp; Beneficiarios. In tres Tomos ſeu Partes diſtributa. Opus ex Sanctis Patribus &amp; Conciliis, ex quorum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Temporum Hiſtoricis decerptum. 3 Vol. Folio, <hi>Pariſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Book being one of the beſt Pieces of this Age and written by one of the moſt eminent in Learning, we ſhall give an account of it in our next.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anglia Sacra;</hi> five Collectio Hiſtoriarum, partim antiquitus, partim recenter ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptarum, de Archi-Epiſcopis &amp; Epiſcopis Angliae, à pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ma Fidei Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuſceptione,
<pb facs="tcp:54947:37"/>ad Annum 1640. nune primum ex MSS Cod. in lucem editarum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s Prim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, de At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Epiſcop Ecoleſiarum quas Monachi poſſiderunt. Edi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re. <hi>Henrico Wharton,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olio <hi>Lond.</hi> Of this we ſhall give a particular account in our next.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edmund. Richerii</hi> Hiſtoria Conciliorum Generalium, in IV Libros diſtributa; &amp; ejuſdem Vindiciae Doctrinae Majorum Scholae Pariſienſ de Authoritate &amp; Infallibilitate Eccleſiae in Rebus Fidei &amp; Morum, contra Defenſores Monarchiae Univerſalis &amp; abſoluta Curiae Romanae, Lib. IV. etiam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Libellus ejus de Eccleſiaſtica &amp; Politica Poteſtate. 7 Tom in Quarto. Which with his late Treatiſe, <hi>de Poteſtate Eccleſiae in Rebus Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralibus,</hi> compleat the Works of this Learned Author.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lud. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ies du Pin</hi> Bibliotheque des Autheurs Eccleſiaſtiques, Quarto. Vol. 4<hi rend="sup">••</hi> &amp; 5<hi rend="sup">um</hi>. <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>paratim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joan. Leuſden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Compendium Graecum Novi Teſtamenti, in quo omnes Univerſi Novi Teſtam. Voces una cum Verſione Latina inveniuntur. Editio ultima ab Authore Recognita &amp; Aucta. <hi>Lugd. Bat.</hi> in Octavo.</p>
            <p>Teſtamentum Novum Latine, <hi>Sebaſtiano Caſtalione</hi> Interprete, cui in Margine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita ſunt Loca parallela S. Script quae <hi>Steph. Curcellaeus</hi> Graecae ſuae Edition. adiunxit necnon Variant. Lection. <hi>Amſt.</hi> Octavo. Well Printed in a fair Character and good Paper; and is by much the faireſt Edition of this eſteemed Book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Petri Gaſſendi</hi> Metaphyſica Diſquiſitio Anti-Carteſiana, ſeu Diſſertationes &amp; Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia adverſus Renati <hi>des Cartes</hi> Medit. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltraj.</hi> 1691 in Octavo.</p>
            <p>D <hi>Aug. Quirin. Rivini</hi> Introductio ad Rem Herbariam CLXXIX. Figur aeneis Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum Rariorum illuſtrata Fol. Charta mag. <hi>Lipſ.</hi> 1691. In which not only the excellent Figures of ſeveral very rare Plants, but the Author's Method, expreſs'd in his general Introduction before the Book, deſerves the eſteem of all the Lovers of Natural Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy.</p>
            <p>Opuſcula Philoſophica; quibus continentur Principia Philoſophiae antiquiſſimae &amp; recentiſſimae, ac Philoſophiae Vulgaris Refutata in duodecimo. <hi>Amſt.</hi> 1691.</p>
            <p>This Book contains Two different Tracts: The Firſt is made up of ſome E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agments found, as tis pretended, in the Cloſet of an Engliſh Counteſs, who by the reading of the ancient Philoſophers, forſook the Opinions of <hi>Des Cartes.</hi> The other hath ſeveral Dialogues between a French and a Spaniſh Philoſopher; in which the Frenchman hath the better of it, and vindicates the new <hi>Hypotheſes,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Authores Claſſici varii cum Interpretatione &amp; Notis Doctiſſimorum Virorum, Juſſu Chriſtianiſimi Regis editi, ad Uſum Sereniſſimi <hi>Delphini,</hi> in Quarto. <hi>Pariſ.</hi> Moſt of which are here to be had.</p>
            <p>Authores ad Uſum <hi>Delphini,</hi> quos juxta Editionem Pariſinam, <hi>Londini</hi> editi ſunt, in Octavo. <hi>viz. Virgilius, Terentius, Horatius, Cornel. Nepos,</hi> &amp; <hi>Juvenal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Proſpect of <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſey.</hi> Colledge, curiouſly drawn, and engraved in a large Copper-Plate, with a Proſpect alſo of the Country contiguous; By <hi>J. Kip,</hi> who deſigns to Publiſh the Draughts of all the King's Houſes.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Books now in the Preſs, which will be Publiſhed in a few Weeks.</head>
               <item>Les Oeuvres d'<hi>Horact,</hi> Lat. &amp; Franc. avec des Remarques par M. <hi>D'Acier.</hi> 10 Vol. in 12.</item>
               <item>Les Comedies de <hi>Plante,</hi> Lat. &amp; Franc avec les Remarques du la Même. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3 Vol. 12.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:54947:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
